<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Natasha&#39;s Journey</title>
    <link>https://natashakatson.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Natasha&#39;s Journey</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 13:35:27 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://natashakatson.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Как мы получали водительские права в Торонто</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/driver-license/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 13:35:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/driver-license/</guid>
      <description>Сегодня хочу рассказать про то, как мы готовились к сдаче экзамена на водительские права. Немного вводных данных - у каждого из нас стаж около 10 лет, нет проблем со зрением, перед отъездом я продала свою любимую Audi и ужасно грущу без машины.
В Онтарио ездить на иностранных правах можно только первые 2 месяца. На самом деле, говорят, что в аренду машину могут давать и дальше, но если остановит коп, то мало не покажется, т.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How We Rented A Condo in Toronto</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/rent/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2021 19:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/rent/</guid>
      <description>Today I&amp;rsquo;ll share my experience of looking for a condo (an apartment) in Toronto. A disclamer: I&amp;rsquo;ll refer to our condo as an apartment just because it sounds more familiar to me.
While we have a temporary place till March 3, we have recently signed a lease to a new place, and we should get the keys on February 17. As a person who has recently moved here from Russia, I still feel that it&amp;rsquo;s all a fraud, but hopefully, this country is more civilized, and a signed lease gives you some guarantees.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Get Your SIN in Canada</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/get-your-sin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 14:54:18 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/get-your-sin/</guid>
      <description>Finally, we have all the necessary documents (work permit, to be specific) to proceed with further bureaucracy.
Here is how the process usually works. A person lands in Canada with a work visa (let&amp;rsquo;s say during the COVID pandemic). After the arrival, they get a Work Permit at the airport and take a two-week quarantine, which I mentioned earlier. While they in quarantine, they can apply online for a SIN (social insurance number0, contact a bank to get an account, and get employed remotely with their Work Permit.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Day When We Finally Got a Work Permit</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/welcome-to-canada/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 20:27:05 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/welcome-to-canada/</guid>
      <description>Today is the 11th of January, which means that we have to go to the airport to check if there are any news regarding our case. I had insomnia, couldn&amp;rsquo;t eat in the morning, but we finally went to the airport to be there by 2:30 pm.
CBSA office looks similar to the police station (I haven&amp;rsquo;t been at any, but I see it that way). The Officer on duty got our documents and checked if we were who we said we were.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quarantine in Toronto </title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/quarantine/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 15:26:31 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/quarantine/</guid>
      <description>While I have some free time, I want to tell you about the quarantine in Canada, specifically in Toronto. Before we went to Canada, we read this article about the 14 days of mandatory quarantine for everyone entering Canada. As requested, we prepared a quarantine plan to share with the Officer, but we haven&amp;rsquo;t talked much about the quarantine itself because of our unusual case. The Officer just told us to go to our temporary place and be back at the airport when the quarantine is over.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Story About One Almost Successful Relocation</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/hello-canada/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 21:19:57 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/hello-canada/</guid>
      <description>Hello, my name is Natasha, and I&amp;rsquo;m a person who plans everything, but nothing goes according to my plan because of very different circumstances (and then I suffer and get depressed). I always wanted to move from Russia. I had plenty of ideas, thoughts, and sometimes opportunities to do that, but it never really happened until this time.
Immigration and relocation is not an easy process, especially during a pandemic. I am sure that many of those who relocated have 1001 stories about how they moved, but ours is just very weird and unusual.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Archive</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.github.io/archives/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.github.io/archives/</guid>
      <description>archives</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
