<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Natasha&#39;s Journey</title>
    <link>https://natashakatson.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Natasha&#39;s Journey</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 20:30:27 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://natashakatson.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Пост про то, как я сдала на права G full</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.com/posts/driver-license-gfull/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 20:30:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.com/posts/driver-license-gfull/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Всем привет!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Да, меня можно наконец поздравить, неделю назад я сдала экзамен на долгожданные G full права! И вот небольшой рассказ про то, как всё произошло.
Это была моя вторая попытка сдать на G full и 4 раз сдачи на права в целом. Я уже рассказывала и про &lt;a href=&#34;https://natashakatson.com/ru/posts/how-to-fail-an-exam/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;первый фейл&lt;/a&gt;, и &lt;a href=&#34;https://natashakatson.com/ru/posts/first-summer-in-canada/#%d0%b2%d0%be%d0%b4%d0%b8%d1%82%d0%b5%d0%bb%d1%8c%d1%81%d0%ba%d0%b8%d0%b5-%d0%bf%d1%80%d0%b0%d0%b2%d0%b0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;про второй и третий заход&lt;/a&gt;. Вкратце, т.к. у меня зачли российский опыт, я могла сразу сдавать на G full, но т.к. завалила первый экзамен, то нужно было пересдать сначала на G2 (сдала со второго раза), а потом уже сдавать на G full.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;как-я-забронировала-дату-экзамена&#34;&gt;Как я забронировала дату экзамена&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Я уже много раз рассказывала про то, что найти дату экзамена в Торонто супер сложно. Дело в том, что здесь больше полугода были закрыты все центры сдачи экзаменов, поэтому очередь из желающих сдать на права получилась огромная. В предыдущие разы однажды мне повезло и когда я в сто пятый раз проверяла сайт, как раз выложили новые даты; однажды помог инструктор; один раз меня отметили в Торонтовском чате, когда увидели свободные окна. Но в этот раз мне совсем не везло, ближайшая дата была на февраль. Я тратила примерно час в день постоянно обновляя страницу и проверяя разные локейшены в пределах 50 км от Торонто, но в течение 2 недель не выпало ни одного места. Поэтому на помощь пришёл Д. и написал скрипт, который за меня искал свободную дату 😄. Пару дней и вуаля, дата нашлась!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Было 3 часа дня, когда нашлась доступная дата на следующий день на 10 утра. Я решила, что даже не буду тревожить инструктора и побежала брать машину в прокат. Вечером того же дня я решила проехаться и потренироваться по маршруту, который доступен на &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/5gmuQzppCwc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;. Маршрут действительно совпадает, я ведь однажды уже не сдала на G full и каталась по тому же маршруту.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;как-сдала-экзамен&#34;&gt;Как сдала экзамен&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;В день экзамена была супер паршивая погода - лил дождь и было очень серо, в общем, всё ощущалось как дома в Питере 🥲. Но на самом деле на этот раз всё прошло гладко: я не волновалась, приехала на своей арендованной машине и по дороге слушала утреннее радио (вспомнились времена, как я ездила на работку), заранее знала маршрут, мне попалась офигенная экзаменатор (это уже 90%) успеха. Я не сделала ни одной ошибки, и со словами “You did a great job!” экзаменатор меня отправила получать мои права.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Я всё ещё считаю, что могла бы сдать с первого раза, если б у экзаменатора было б нормальное настроение в тот день, видимо.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Кстати, когда приезжаешь в Drivetest сдавать на права, нужно обязательно запарковаться на нумерованное место, т.к. при регистрации на экзамен нужно указать номер машины и номер парковки, чтобы экзаменатор мог легко вас найти. Так вот, всем суеверным посвящается!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://natashakatson.com/images/Gfull/car.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;А ещё, пока сидите в машине и ждёте экзаменатора, необходимо быть в маске, даже если вы одни в машине. Если экзаменатор подойдёт, а вы будете в этот момент без маски, то он/она не будут принимать экзамен.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;цены&#34;&gt;Цены&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Я всегда рада поделиться ценами для общего понимания ситуации. В целом, после завалов экзаменов я ощущала себя примерно так&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://natashakatson.com/images/Gfull/R1O.gif&#34;
         alt=&#34;&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Гос.пошлина:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;G1: 106 CAD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;G2: 53.75 CAD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;G full: 91.25 CAD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Уроки с инструктором: 60 CAD за урок. Я брала 3 урока: два до фейла и один после.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Экзамен с инструктором: 225 CAD первый раз, 300 CAD второй раз т.к. экзамен был загородом (в Brampton), 170 CAD в третий раз (сделал скидку т.к. я постоянный клиент хаха). В экзамен с инструктором входит час поездки до экзамена (чтобы &amp;ldquo;набить руку&amp;rdquo; и морально подготовиться) и машина на сам экзамен. Если на руках G1, то машину в прокат не взять, поэтому приходится нанимать инструктора с его машиной на сам экзамен.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Снять машину на экзамен G full: 134 CAD. У меня уже были на руках права G2, поэтому смогла спокойно взять машину в прокат.
&lt;strong&gt;Итого&lt;/strong&gt;: 1260 CAD. Столько я потратила, учитывая, что последние 10 лет ездила на машине и нужно было “просто обновить права”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;инструктор&#34;&gt;Инструктор&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Несмотря на мои фейлы, инструктор был классный и я ему ужасно благодарна! Его рекомендуют во всех местных чатиках. Инструктора зовут Игорь, у него есть своя &lt;a href=&#34;https://g.page/sprint-driving?share&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;автошкола&lt;/a&gt;, где они обучают с нуля или готовят иммигрантов и не только сдавать здесь экзамены. Д. сдал с первого раза, взяв всего один урок (как и большинство иммигрантов). Я всячески рекомендую взять инструктора хотя бы на один урок - просто, чтобы узнать местные требования к сдаче экзамена. Например, повороты на красный направо, постоянно крутить головой, чтобы проверять мёртвые зоны при любых перестроениях и прочее. Наши привычки могут очень сильно отличаться от местных требований. Из минусов, для уроков нужно ездить в North York, но ради пары уроков это того явно стоит.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ну а теперь можно выдохнуть и наслаждаться своими полноценными правами автомобилиста! Последний раз я так радовалась в 2008, когда получила свои водительские права.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S. Если нужна ссылка на скрипт, можете оставить комментарий под этим постом или в чате &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.me/natashakatson&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Телеграм&lt;/a&gt;, где я публикую новые посты.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How We Rented A Condo in Toronto</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.com/posts/rent/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2021 19:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.com/posts/rent/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I&amp;rsquo;ll share my experience of looking for a condo (an apartment) in Toronto. A disclamer: I&amp;rsquo;ll refer to our condo as an apartment just because it sounds more familiar to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we have a temporary place till March 3, we have recently signed a lease to a new place, and we should get the keys on February 17. As a person who has recently moved here from Russia, I still feel that it&amp;rsquo;s all a fraud, but hopefully, this country is more civilized, and a signed lease gives you some guarantees. It&amp;rsquo;s a long read, but I really tried to explain in details how everything works here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-1---learn-about-the-city&#34;&gt;Step 1 - learn about the city&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few weeks before moving to Toronto, we decided to learn a little bit about its neighborhoods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, I emailed my friend who moved to Toronto 16 years ago (and we haven&amp;rsquo;t talked much since then). I asked him to divide the city into several zones, where red would show the areas that it&amp;rsquo;s better to avoid, and green would show friendly neighborhoods. And I got the following image from him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://natashakatson.com/images/areas.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;areas&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then we found a &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/aCLEoLEzUZs&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; on YouTube about the five best neighborhoods in Toronto where a guy shared details about different areas and whether it&amp;rsquo;s possible to get there without a car. We added all the neighborhoods to Google maps to check them out later when we actually move to Toronto.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I asked about nice neighborhoods in a Russian &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.me/canada_it&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;channel&lt;/a&gt; on Telegram about the Tech industry in Canada. They recommended me the following areas: High Park, Humber Bay Shores, Mimico, Roncesvalles, Sunnyside. We also added those places to Google maps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-2---explore-the-neighborhoods&#34;&gt;Step 2 - explore the neighborhoods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we only got work permits after a month and a half of being in Canada, we had enough time to check out the city after the quarantine.
I was pretty disappointed with Toronto&amp;rsquo;s architecture; the city has many skyscrapers, most of them are high-rise condo-buildings, not even the offices. I once lived in a tall building in St.Petersburg, and I hated it. Of course, condo-buildings here are different: they have a swimming pool, a gym, a concierge service, but living in a high-rise building is rarely a pleasure (at least that&amp;rsquo;s how I feel).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another essential thing to us was transport accessibility. Like the USA, Canada is a country built for cars, but Toronto is partially covered by the subway. We would gladly buy a car and rent a house somewhere outside of the city, but our license here in Ontario is only valid for the first two months after arrival, and due to COVID-19, driving exams have been canceled. Even when the offices reopen, the queues there are already for six months ahead. Therefore, it was important for us to choose an area so we can comfortably live there without a car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After we got out of quarantine, we went to explore the areas. At first, we took the subway, but then we realized that it was not a productive way to explore the city. Therefore, we decided to rent a car for a day and go around all the previously marked areas in Google maps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very first area that we saw was &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/High&amp;#43;Park/@43.641955,-79.4554729,14.03z/data=!4m5!3m4!1s0x882b35d32336f705:0x1bcc825a300ee67!8m2!3d43.6465479!4d-79.4636903&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;High Park&lt;/a&gt; and everything around it. I really liked it there: low houses, a huge park, shops, restaurants, bars, a subway line. I won&amp;rsquo;t say that the area is close to the downtown, it&amp;rsquo;s about half an hour away from it. And it is unlikely that we will need to go to downtown a lot with offices being closed and everything. Other areas were not that great: some of them had mostly old houses, which we could not rent anyway because it makes no sense and it&amp;rsquo;s too expensive to rent a whole house for two of us; others only had high-rise buildings (for example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps?q=humber&amp;#43;bay&amp;amp;um=1&amp;amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwj8ntSI9c7uAhUGElkFHdqbDSsQ_AUoAXoECBcQAw&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Humber Bay Shore&lt;/a&gt;); some areas were cozy but difficult to get to without a car (for example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Long&amp;#43;Branch,&amp;#43;Toronto,&amp;#43;ON/@43.5912977,-79.5425108,15z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x882b484122f10ee1:0x18d94d109b9f2dc8!8m2!3d43.593421!4d-79.538164&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Long Branch&lt;/a&gt;). As for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Mississauga,&amp;#43;ON/@43.5772409,-79.6344311,11z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x882b469fe76b05b7:0x3146cbed75966db!8m2!3d43.5890452!4d-79.6441198&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mississauga&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Oakville,&amp;#43;ON/@43.466272,-79.8334236,11z/data=!4m5!3m4!1s0x882b5b8b8f729979:0x5037b28c7231bd0!8m2!3d43.467517!4d-79.6876659&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Oakville&lt;/a&gt;, these are two very nice towns that are located close to Toronto but it seemed inconvenient to live there without a car, even though the variety of places for rent there is huge and housing is cheaper than in the city.
My favorite neighborhood was &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Bridle&amp;#43;Path,&amp;#43;Toronto,&amp;#43;ON/@43.7340798,-79.3768215,15z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x89d4cd39eae61e4b:0xf462ffb9f7f22860!8m2!3d43.7359137!4d-79.3718986&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bridle Path&lt;/a&gt;, but we wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be able to rent anything there 🥲. Various celebrities live in that area, for example, Drake (and his house is worth about $100 million CAD). We didn&amp;rsquo;t consider renting a place in downtown because although all the offices, the lake, and other entertainment places are located there, there are still too many homeless people, high-rise buildings, and it&amp;rsquo;s generally uncomfortable to live there if you ask me. After all, downtown in North America and Europe differs a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-3---learn-about-different-types-of-housing&#34;&gt;Step 3 - learn about different types of housing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toronto is huge and wildly different; you can find completely different types of housing for rent. Here is an overview:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A condo. Usually, a condo is owned by a person, in rare cases by some company. There are two types of condo buildings: high-rise and low-rise. As I wrote above, these buildings also have some amenities, and the apartments, in general, look modern. We decided to rent a place in a high-rise building only if we don&amp;rsquo;t find anything else. But a condo as a type of rental housing was just right for us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rental apartments that are located in buildings that are owned by a company. Pros - you don&amp;rsquo;t need to communicate with a landlord if something needs to be fixed; cons - usually, the washer and a dryer are located in those buildings&#39; basement. Also, we heard there might be bedbugs in such buildings. So we decided even not to consider such places, although they are in great demand among people who have just arrived in Canada.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basements - are my &amp;ldquo;favorite&amp;rdquo; type of rental housing here. If you see a house in Toronto, most probably someone lives in a basement there (and it&amp;rsquo;s not a homeless person!). They say homeowners rent out basements to pay for their mortgage, not sure if it&amp;rsquo;s true because often the first and the second floors are also rented out. Even though you&amp;rsquo;ll most likely have a backyard if you rent a basement, it&amp;rsquo;s dark inside, and come on.. it&amp;rsquo;s a basement! We did not consider the basements at all; it still seems to me that it is not very healthy to live there (particularly for the lungs).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The floor in a house or a whole house. Everything is clear here, the landlord will own the place, but since houses are larger than the condos, they&amp;rsquo;ll be more pricy. I always wanted to rent a house, but it didn&amp;rsquo;t fit into the budget at all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Townhouse. Usually, a townhouse is a detached house and only has neighbours from the side. It&amp;rsquo;s a bit different here; they basically call any apartment in two to three storeys buildings a townhouse. If it is located on the first floor, it most likely has a terrace; if it&amp;rsquo;s located on the last floor, it has an entrance to the roof. The second floor is not that lucky, there is nothing there 🙂. We would definitely rent a  townhouse, but they are pretty pricy in the areas where you can get without a car. I haven&amp;rsquo;t seen any decent townhouses for less than $3500 CAD.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-4---prepare-to-rent-a-place&#34;&gt;Step 4 - prepare to rent a place&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we finally got our documents to stay here in Canada legally, we could start preparations to rent a place. Why do you need to prepare everything in advance? Well, good places are rented out too quickly here, so you need to have all the documents on you by the time you want to actually rent a place. Here is a list of documents for those who come to Canada as a foreign worker:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An employment letter that states the salary. If you don&amp;rsquo;t have it, a valid job offer might also work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A work permit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A recommendation letter from a bank (we got one back in Russia).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And the most important thing - you should have enough money in your Canadian bank account. Firstly, to get a statement from a local bank that you have money, and secondly, so that you can make a deposit within 24 hours after signing the contract (I&amp;rsquo;ll talk more about it later).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some landlords also want to see your SIN, but it&amp;rsquo;s illegal, and you should not do it.
A few days after D. got employed here, we opened a bank account, transferred our funds from Russia, and got a check book that could be helpful later for rent payments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-5---actually-rent-a-place&#34;&gt;Step 5 - actually rent a place&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, when we got all the documents, we could start looking for a place. I should also mention that you can&amp;rsquo;t move out earlier than in a year when you rent a place in Toronto. If you do, you will still have to pay till the end of the lease period anyway. So it was vital for us to find a decent place where we would enjoy living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our relocation consultant introduced us to an agent would help us with all the lease related paperwork. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to pay for an agent here, the landlord does it even if you hired an agent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several sites where you can look for an apartment, but the most popular (in my opinion) are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.realtor.ca/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;realtor.ca&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://condos.ca/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;condos.ca&lt;/a&gt;. On condos.ca, you can also check the history of a particular apartment. For example, you can find the apartment&amp;rsquo;s price when it was rented out previously. Our agent Aine has also recommented &lt;a href=&#34;https://realestate.love/home?presented-by=00f1adb36bbd4841ab6b26ee7600d6dd&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;realestate.love&lt;/a&gt; app, if you register with this &lt;a href=&#34;https://realestate.love/home?presented-by=00f1adb36bbd4841ab6b26ee7600d6dd&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;, Aine will be assigned as your realtor, and she is great!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even before we moved to Toronto, we decided that we could afford to spend around $2500 CAD on rent. We wanted to rent a 2-bedroom apartment, because now when we work from home, we need a space for home office. They say that during the lockdown, real estate prices in the city have dropped significantly. But in fact, it hit the downtown condos mostly because people no longer need to live near offices, but unfortunately, it did not really affect other areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After we checked all of the areas mentioned above, we decided to look at the High Park area and everything around it (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Bloor&amp;#43;West&amp;#43;Village,&amp;#43;Toronto,&amp;#43;ON/data=!4m2!3m1!1s0x882b3687bf4111a9:0x547e7e8c155e92b1?sa=X&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwiUu-OL-c7uAhUHGFkFHTdZCCsQ8gEwNXoECCQQAQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bloor West&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/The&amp;#43;Junction,&amp;#43;Toronto,&amp;#43;ON/@43.6665206,-79.4794536,15z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x882b3423ddb31365:0x52d8c657a0a69c40!8m2!3d43.6655088!4d-79.4721328&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Junction&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/High&amp;#43;Park&amp;#43;North,&amp;#43;Toronto,&amp;#43;ON/@43.6580291,-79.4749742,15z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x882b3426203a9f13:0x341044bd3bac1ae2!8m2!3d43.6572262!4d-79.4668306&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;High Park North&lt;/a&gt;). But due to the absence of high-rises (which is a pro), there were very few options available for rent (which is a con). I monitored rental sites for about a month (I looked for the sake of interest even before we could rent something) and rarely saw any options there. There are a lot of basements available but no condos. Finally, I saw a charming condo that met all our criteria: a 2-bedroom, low-rise building, bright place with a balcony. The price was $2700 CAD, and it was fine for us (everything that I really liked was above $3000 CAD anyway). We realized that the apartment was nice, the area was excellent (Junction, which is a little further from High Park than we planned, but it was still ok), and we immediately contacted our agent. I want to mention that there was a huge selection of apartments in high-rise buildings, but not so many in low-rise buildings in different areas. In fact, it was the only option that we liked in the whole city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday night, the landlord&amp;rsquo;s agent agreed to show us the place on Saturday morning. Despite a couple of cons, for example, there are no windows in one bedroom, and there is also no concierge in the house, we really liked the place, and we wanted to rent it badly. Speaking of the bedroom without the windows. It looks like the developers have found a way to trick the system into making a room with a glass sliding door that lets in enough light to be recognized by local regulations as a bedroom. Surprisingly developers here act like in Russia and gain maximum profit from every square meter.
The agent also warned us that some other people would also check the place on Sunday, so it would be better to send our offer to the landlord as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-6---survive-the-bureaucracy&#34;&gt;Step 6 - survive the bureaucracy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a timeline to clarify how difficult everything is here and how different from the usual renting process in St. Petersburg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday, 11 am. We checked the place, liked it and decided to rent it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday, 12 pm. Right after we checked the apartments, we got into the agent&amp;rsquo;s car (all cafes are closed here) and filled out our offer for renting an apartment (OREA Form 410), which our agent later added to Docusign for signing (it&amp;rsquo;s very cool that the entire document flow here can be done online). The landlord will only consider you as a tenant if they receive an offer from you (well, from their agent). In the offer, you need to add all tenants and occupants, your position and company details, previous place of residence, and two contacts in Canada as referrals. We only have one friend in Vancouver, so we added her, and we decided to add a friend from the USA.
Although usually, the rent starts on the 1st of the month, our possession date will be February 17. Current tenants occupy the place until February 15, so we decided to rent the apartment right after they leave. Basically, in our offer, we proposed to pay for a year and a few weeks on top and three months of deposits instead of the usual two months (our agent said that since we don&amp;rsquo;t have any credit history in Canada, it might help us to get the place). Then the agent got our documents altogether and emailed them to the landlord&amp;rsquo;s agent along with our offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday, 6 pm. We received an email from our agent saying that the other agent didn&amp;rsquo;t want to forward our offer to the landlord. They asked for a confirmation from D.&amp;rsquo;s company that he was employed there and passed a probation period. And since it was Saturday, they proposed to wait until Monday to get a response from the HR team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday, 7 pm. D. emailed both HR and the team lead and asked them to confirm his employment ASAP. It was complicated to confirm the probation period, though. He had already passed the probation period in Russia, but since he was a new employee here in Canada, HR were obligated to add another probation period to the contract. Moreover, that agent shouldn&amp;rsquo;t even ask about the probation period since it&amp;rsquo;s a piece of confidential information. Our agent just assumed that the landlord&amp;rsquo;s agent didn&amp;rsquo;t want to do any paperwork on the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sunday, 7 pm. Our agent told us that other people who also checked the condo made an offer, and she assumed that they offered $2800 CAD. We got really sad, but the agent said it was a typical situation in Toronto, and, if we wanted, we could raise our offer to $2900 CAD. She said that $2900 CAD was the initial price for that place before COVID, and it really might help. We rechecked the real estate websites, realized there was nothing new, and decided to go with a new price (although, as I previously mentioned, our initial limit was $2500 CAD). We were also worried that the landlord&amp;rsquo;s agent wouldn&amp;rsquo;t even forward our offer to the landlord, but our agent assured us that they were obligated by law to forward all offers they received.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monday, 3 pm. The landlord chose us! We were thrilled that our (mine) misery during the weekend was not in vain (well, as usual, I didn&amp;rsquo;t sleep and didn&amp;rsquo;t eat well). Our agent immediately warned us that when the landlord signs the offer, the apartment is &amp;ldquo;frozen&amp;rdquo; on the market; roughly speaking, they have no right to show or lease it to anyone. Then the most interesting thing began - they sent us a 20 pages contract, we signed it. And then, the landlord&amp;rsquo;s agent added an appendix B to the contract, yet another 20 pages long. As our agent said, everything in the add-on looked like we were renting a house, not a condo, i.e., they wanted to add as much as possible into the contract to keep themselves safe (I can understand it, but some things were just crazy). Some statements were completely contrary to the law of the state of Ontario, which means they had no legal value. For example, it stated that no pets were allowed in the apartment (we don&amp;rsquo;t have any pets, though). Well, everyone in Ontario is allowed to have pets; in fact, a gorgeous kitty lives in this apartment at the moment 😸.
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://natashakatson.com/images/cat.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;кот&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

Another &amp;ldquo;cool&amp;rdquo; thing was about the carpet. &amp;ldquo;The Tenant agrees to employ carpets for frequent walking areas in order to prevent noise
distribution and floor deterioration.&amp;rdquo; Our agent told us that this part usually applies to the houses, but not to the condos.
Generally, we wanted to remove some statements from the contract, but then we learned how it works. We can either accept the contract and sign as is or reject and ask to send a new contract with the desired changes. But, if you reject the current contract (i.e., just ask to change any statements there), the apartment is again open to the market, and at that moment, someone can make another offer, which may be better than ours, and in this case, we would lose our apartment. So we agreed with everything and signed the contract as is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After both parties have signed the contract, you as a tenant have one working day to make a deposit. The apartment is considered to be leased the moment the landlord&amp;rsquo;s brokerage receives the deposit. The deposit does not go directly to the landlord to protect all parties from fraud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday morning, we went to the bank to make a deposit. We had two options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To electronically wire the funds, but this option costs an additional $17.50 CAD;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To deliver a bank draft in person to the bank, which is free. We chose this option, went to our bank, got a check, made a picture of it (in case the other bank loses it, yes, it happens!), and delivered the check to another bank.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday afternoon, we sent the picture of the check to our agent, and after a few hours got an update that the brokerage received our deposit. At that moment, we officially rented that condo!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hurray, now we need to wait for February 17 and get the keys. Not yet :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-7---do-a-million-more-things-to-get-the-keys-to-the-apartment&#34;&gt;Step 7 - do a million more things to get the keys to the apartment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After our agent congratulated us on a successful deal (she knew how we were worried and periodically called me to find out how I felt 🥲), we received an email from our relocation consultant with the next steps. In order for the landlord to give us the keys, we had to do a few more things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Purchase tenant&amp;rsquo;s insurance. We called different companies for a quote but then learned that D&amp;rsquo;s company provides a TD Insurance discount. We had to add liability coverage for $1 000 000 CAD based on our lease, and we also added some water damage coverage. After the discount, the final price was $405 CAD, including tax.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had to move the electricity and water account over to our names. That was easy; we just registered on the website which our consultant has provided us with. Starting from February 17, we will have access to our account.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contact our landlord regarding the payment method. We had two options again:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Email transfer. We preferred this option, but RBC has a $2500 CAD limit per day for any transfers, and it&amp;rsquo;s not enough for us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post-dated checks.  So we chose this option since we also already got the checks when we opened an account.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prepare a personal check for $300 CAD refundable key deposit (yes, if we lose our keys, we would have to pay $300 CAD for it).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And my favorite part is that we have to reserve an elevator for our move with building management (it&amp;rsquo;s just something very new to us!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-epilogue&#34;&gt;An epilogue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have read up to this point, my congratulations to you 😂🥳. I&amp;rsquo;m thrilled that we managed to rent the apartment that we liked and in the area where we wanted to live. The only thing we absolutely forgot to do was to check if there were any shelters in the area. There are many mentally sick homeless people in Toronto, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to interact with them, and having a shelter nearby means they will continuously hang around. I just remembered this yesterday and discovered that there is the second-largest shelter in Toronto for homeless women not far from the condo building. I was very upset, but let&amp;rsquo;s hope that everything will be fine there because after all the area is still considered quite nice and even trendy 😏.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also want to say that I honestly admire those who come to Canada without work and any help. I can say that the consultant helps a lot by telling us what to do and when. When you first come across such an ordinary situation as renting an apartment, you get a little crazy about everything that needs to be done in a new country. I immediately remembered how we moved out of our apartment in St. Petersburg. We told our landlord about us leaving two weeks before we moved out. We told her that our friends wanted to move in, introduced them, and they paid us the deposit that she owned us, not to bother the landlord once again. Haha, here they probably only write about it in fairy tales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still have the feeling that it&amp;rsquo;s all scam before we actually get the keys. Oh, I need to get rid of this post-Russian habit of seeing a fraud everywhere or at least relax for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Get Your SIN in Canada</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.com/posts/get-your-sin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 14:54:18 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.com/posts/get-your-sin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Finally, we have all the necessary documents (work permit, to be specific) to proceed with further bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is how the process usually works. A person lands in Canada with a work visa (let&amp;rsquo;s say during the COVID pandemic). After the arrival, they get a Work Permit at the airport and take a two-week quarantine, which I &lt;a href=&#34;https://natashakatson.github.io/ru/posts/quarantine/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;mentioned&lt;/a&gt; earlier. While they in quarantine, they can apply online for a SIN (social insurance number0, contact a bank to get an account, and get employed remotely with their Work Permit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, the minimum required documents before you can start looking for an apartment are: SIN, a bank account, employment confirmation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we spent a month and a half in Canada in the &amp;ldquo;waiting&amp;rdquo; status and only got Work Permits a few days ago, we couldn&amp;rsquo;t apply anywhere. Therefore, as soon as we received the Work Permit on January 11, we immediately started to work on further steps. And we started with a SIN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our relocation package also included a local consultant, so we have been assigned with a consultant named M. who would help us with local affairs upon our arrival. M. advised us to apply for a SIN online. For some reason, to apply online, one needs either an employment letter (and the company will only hire D. on January 20) or a confirmation address (and we don&amp;rsquo;t have a permanent address yet). Also, some people who applied online bragged about their SIN being lost in the mail. And it takes them a month to issue a SIN for those who apply online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We decided that M.&amp;rsquo;s advice to apply online was, of course, a good one, and we would use it if necessary. But we decided to try to go to the Service Canada office first (offline). We checked the addresses for open offices &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.servicecanada.gc.ca/tbsc-fsco/sc-dsp.jsp?rc=3591&amp;amp;lang=eng&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and decided to try our fortune (I already forgot what does this word even mean..fortune). I find it funny that they say on the website that the shortest waiting time is from 8:30 till 10:00 am. We went there at 8:30, and we were the only ones. How does it work? If people read that there are no lines during these hours, why don&amp;rsquo;t they go there exactly from 8:30 - 10:00 am? :) It&amp;rsquo;s a rhetorical question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;here-is-a-cool-story&#34;&gt;Here is a cool story&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you read a previous &lt;a href=&#34;https://natashakatson.github.io/ru/posts/welcome-to-canada/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;, you probably know that our passports got stamped only on January 11 (the same as Work Permit).
Here we are at Service Canada; I start talking with the representative and giving her my passport and Work Permit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The representative: [shocked]. Omg, did you arrive in Canada the day before yesterday?! &lt;br&gt;
Me: [also shocked for a sec] Oh, no, no, no, no! We arrived on December 3.&lt;br&gt;
She: But your passport was stamped on January 11! You should quarantine at home!&lt;br&gt;
Me: No, no, no, no, no! We arrived on December 3, we quarantined, but they only issued our Work Permits and stamped our passports on January 11.&lt;br&gt;
She: ..but where did you get your Work Permit and a stamp?!&lt;br&gt;
Me: At the airport, we got back there after the quarantine because we had an appointment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She listened and immediately asked about some confirmation to make sure that we arrived on December 3. Of course, we didn&amp;rsquo;t have any proof: the Officer took our appointment paper; the ArriveCan app doesn&amp;rsquo;t store history (wtf?!); nobody signed the declaration form that we filled out at the plane, and we didn&amp;rsquo;t have our tickets on us. But then we remembered that we do have a copy of the appointment paper in the email, so we showed it. The representatives at Office Canada believed us but couldn&amp;rsquo;t issue a SIN. The system said that we should stay at home for two weeks and shouldn&amp;rsquo;t walk around to get our documents. But then a miracle happened, we finally met friendly people. Those women told us not to worry, that they really wanted to help us and would do their best to do so. And, after half an hour and a talk with their manager, they issued us our SINs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you need to get a SIN, I strongly recommend going directly to the Service Canada office. One of the perks is that they do not require any proof of address; Work Permit and a passport should be enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S. After my previous experience, I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect to meet friendly people at the Government office (I even left a nice review on Google Maps). On the way home, some construction worker said &amp;ldquo;good morning&amp;rdquo; and smiled. Later on the same day, we opened bank accounts, but without a credit card yet (you need an employment letter to get one). I even managed to finally get a sim card (e sim) at &lt;a href=&#34;https://referme.to/nataliiak-30n&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Fido&lt;/a&gt; and used one of their promos on time (12 G.B. for $55 which is still a lot but it&amp;rsquo;s cheaper than the usual $75 for 12 G.B.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turned out to be a productive and enjoyable day. Isn&amp;rsquo;t that wonderful?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Day When We Finally Got a Work Permit</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.com/posts/welcome-to-canada/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 20:27:05 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.com/posts/welcome-to-canada/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today is the 11th of January, which means that we have to go to the airport to check if there are any news regarding our &lt;a href=&#34;https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/hello-canada/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;case&lt;/a&gt;. I had insomnia, couldn&amp;rsquo;t eat in the morning, but we finally went to the airport to be there by 2:30 pm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CBSA office looks similar to the police station (I haven&amp;rsquo;t been at any, but I see it that way). The Officer on duty got our documents and checked if we were who we said we were. He looked at D.&amp;rsquo;s copy of the passport, looked at me, and said: &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s not you&amp;rdquo;. Of course, it&amp;rsquo;s not me; it&amp;rsquo;s my husband&amp;rsquo;s ID you are looking at, Officer. Then he asked us about our story, and when we told him, he got confused. He asked D.: &amp;ldquo;How will I know that it&amp;rsquo;s you and not your tween brother?&amp;rdquo; I kind of wanted to cry when I heard this question. Really? Really? How about checking all the supporting documents and biometrics for a change. Then we told him that we have been waiting for a month and a half already, and we really wanted to hear their answer on our case. We also mentioned the last name of the first officer we met upon our arrival here, and luckily he was at the airport that day. The Officer on duty took our documents and went to talk to Officer J. (the one who met us upon our arrival).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After an hour, Officer J. came to us and said there was still no reply from the visa office, but our lawyer convinced him to issue our documents! So, Officer J. decided to issue D. a temporary resident permit, and because of that, he could issue a temporary work permit. Actually, we asked him for the exact same documents when we arrived, but he refused back then. Luckily (we are very grateful), he eventually issued us our papers and gave our passports back with the stamp! We spent an additional $440 CAD ($155 for a new work permit, $200 for a temporary residence permit, $85 for a new biometric). Of course, we didn&amp;rsquo;t care about the prices; we were just happy to stay here in Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They stamped our passports with today&amp;rsquo;s date, which means that we left St.Petersburg on the 3d of December 2020 and arrived in Toronto on the 11th of January, 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a terribly exhausting and rather useless time, but we are happy that bureaucratic situation was resolved in our favor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, now, we can start to deal with life.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quarantine in Toronto </title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.com/posts/quarantine/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 15:26:31 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.com/posts/quarantine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While I have some free time, I want to tell you about the quarantine in Canada, specifically in Toronto. Before we went to Canada, we read this &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.canada.ca/en/public-health/services/publications/diseases-conditions/2019-novel-coronavirus-information-sheet.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; about the 14 days of mandatory quarantine for everyone entering Canada. As requested, we prepared a quarantine plan to share with the Officer, but we haven&amp;rsquo;t talked much about the quarantine itself because of our &lt;a href=&#34;https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/hello-canada/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;unusual case&lt;/a&gt;. The Officer just told us to go to our temporary place and be back at the airport when the quarantine is over. I was actually mentally prepared for the quarantine; what I was not prepared for was our situation. But I won&amp;rsquo;t talk about it today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We got Uber and went directly to our place in downtown Toronto. D.&amp;rsquo;s company rented apartments there in a tall condo building. We knew nothing about the place; we just hoped it would have a balcony so we could &amp;ldquo;walk around and get some air.&amp;rdquo; It appeared to be nice furnished apartments with cooking supplies and everything a person needs to stay at home. It also had a balcony with a view on a small park.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://natashakatson.com/images/2021-01-03.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we arrived, the receptionist told us about the quarantine and added us to the &amp;ldquo;quarantine list,&amp;rdquo; which allowed them to leave the deliveries at our door. Usually, they would ask the residents to pick up the deliveries at the reception (because of Covid). The quarantine means that you should not leave your apartments even if you need to take out the trash. We usually called a company which owned our suit in advance to ask them to take out our trash, put the trash next at our door, and some person picked it up. Every morning we checked-in in the ArriveCan app, which you need to install before going to Canada; either way, they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t let you on board. If you forget to check-in, you&amp;rsquo;ll get a reminder about it. On the 15th day, our profile got reset, and we could finally go outside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now I&amp;rsquo;ll share details about some delivery services that we used to survive the quarantine. There are many deliveries here, but it&amp;rsquo;s not easy to quickly get around them with a full understanding of prices and fees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TL;DR The cheapest way is to order a lot of items directly from the Grocery store. But because of our situation, we were not sure how many things we should order because we didn&amp;rsquo;t know if we would stay here in Canada. So we tried different options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;grocery-delivery&#34;&gt;Grocery Delivery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;uber-eats&#34;&gt;Uber Eats&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next morning after we arrived, we were too hungry to look around for new apps, we had to quickly order something. We were already familiar with &lt;a href=&#34;https://ubereats.app.link/LfdZFuf8Kcb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Uber Eats&lt;/a&gt;. The grocery delivery in Uber Eats is actually powered by Cornershop (I will tell about it further) and is done within 1-2 hours. Eventually, Uber Eats turned out to be the most expensive grocery delivery because we paid both the Uber Eats fee and the Cornershop fee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the summary of our first order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Walmart (grocery itself)&lt;/strong&gt; CA $132.03&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cornershop service CA $13.20&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivery CA $6.90&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Estimated taxes CA $4.47:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product taxes CA $1.85&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Service fee taxes CA $1.72&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivery fee taxes CA $0.90&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Order total&lt;/strong&gt; CA $156.60&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it&amp;rsquo;s pretty expensive, but it&amp;rsquo;s ok when you are hungry, stressed out, and can&amp;rsquo;t go out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later I found out that Uber has recently bought Cornershop, but you can still order groceries directly in Cornershop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cornershop&#34;&gt;Cornershop&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://corner.shop/r/oypnskrr4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Cornershop&lt;/a&gt; also deliver groceries within 1-2 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can order groceries from various supermarkets: Walmart, Costco, Longos, Metro, etc. You also get three free deliveries after the registration. For some reason, they also gifted me a $20 discount, maybe because I added some items to the basket but didn&amp;rsquo;t order them right away. Even though Cornershop charges a 10% service fee for every order, it&amp;rsquo;s still cheaper than Uber Eats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the summary of our first order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Walmart&lt;/strong&gt; $79.40&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cornershop service $7.90&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivery Fee Free&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Estimated taxes: $4.04
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product taxes $3.01&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Service fee taxes $1.03&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Credits applied -$20.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt; $71.38&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We later ordered groceries from Cornershop a few more times, I also shared a referral with my husband, and after we placed an order from his account, I got $20 off for my next order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please note that if some items are out of stock, they will suggest a replacement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;walmart&#34;&gt;Walmart&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another delivery that we tried was Walmart delivery. The downside is that you have to place your order a few days before the actual delivery date. But even after you place your order, you can still manage your basket. For example, the delivery was set for noon, but I could change items in my basket until 10 pm of the previous day. Walmart doesn&amp;rsquo;t charge you for service fee, the standard delivery costs $7.97, but you can order the same-day delivery for $10. Unfortunately, if some items are out of stock, you can&amp;rsquo;t choose the replacement; they will do it for you. But if you don&amp;rsquo;t like it, you can always return it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the summary of our first order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Items Subtotal&lt;/strong&gt;: $130.77&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivery fee :  $7.97&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HST @ 13%:  $2.20&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;: $140.94&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;instacart&#34;&gt;Instacart&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last but not least grocery delivery that I want to mention is &lt;a href=&#34;https://inst.cr/t/YjVsWUdYMTBu&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Instacart&lt;/a&gt;. My referral link will give you a $10 discount for your first order. I also used a referral link when I signed up, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t order items from my basket right away..And I got $20 off the next day :) The delivery costs around 5% of the order summary. I liked it that they contacted me in their virtual chat about the items that were out of stock; this way, it was easier for me to find a replacement. As I previously mentioned, Uber Eats and Cornershop do the same thing, but Instacart representative contact you directly in live chat, which is nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Summary:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Item Subtotal: $93.62&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sales Tax: $0.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tip: $4.68&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Service Fee: $4.68&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bags Fee: $0.30&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Retailer Coupon Discount: -$20.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total: $83.89&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the products were carefully packed, the delivery person left the bags right by the door, knocked, and left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;food-delivery&#34;&gt;Food delivery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from cooking our meals, we also wanted to try various local restaurant deliveries, especially given that Toronto is famous for a variety of cuisine from all over the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We mostly used Uber Eats and DoorDash during our quarantine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;uber-eats-1&#34;&gt;Uber Eats&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ubereats.app.link/LfdZFuf8Kcb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Uber Eats&lt;/a&gt; has a much more variety of restaurants compared to DoorDash. They also have different discounts and personalized offers, for example, the &amp;ldquo;order one, get one free&amp;rdquo; deal. Although it should be the same meal to use this option, we left a comment for a restaurant to make one meal spicier than another one when we ordered from a Thai restaurant. Please note that the price for the meal is usually lower than it actually costs. For example, you want to order Massaman Curry, the price is $21, but you &lt;strong&gt;have to&lt;/strong&gt; add meat/seafood and rice to the order, and you have to separately pay for it. In the end, the &amp;ldquo;order one get one free&amp;rdquo; deal is only applied to Masaman Curry ($21) and is not applied to the additional stuff. There are also different fees applied to the order, like taxes, tips, and service fees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an example of our first order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Massaman Curry&lt;/strong&gt; CA $21&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shrimp CA $4.00&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jasmine Rice CA $0.00 (usually it&amp;rsquo;s not free, though)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tax CA $3.93&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Service Fee CA $4.20&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delivery Fee $0.99&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tips CA $5.11&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt; CA $39.23&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, although the Curry costs $21, we had to pay $39.12 in total. We later noticed that we could modify the tip, but I advise you to leave good tips because it&amp;rsquo;s a pandemic going on, and delivery people are our heroes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Useful tip&lt;/strong&gt;. You can get a free one month trial for Uber Eats (Eats Pass) and get free delivery in addition to 5% off from the orders that are more than $15. I eventually subscribed for Eats Pass for a month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;doordash&#34;&gt;DoorDash&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://drd.sh/iVyp4q/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Doordash&lt;/a&gt; is an Uber Eats competitor. It seemed to me that there are fewer restaurant options in it, but there are promotions, and delivery is often cheaper. DoorDash also has a subscription with some discounts. As a new user, you will get some bonuses - free shipping and some other discounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my first order from DoorDash:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Subtotal&lt;/strong&gt; $30.58&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tax $4.42&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivery Fee Free&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Service Fee $3.36&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discount -$5.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tip $2.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt; $35.36&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;alcohol-delivery&#34;&gt;Alcohol delivery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also order alcohol in Toronto. We used &lt;a href=&#34;https://runnerinc.page.link/DgAEw6CcoQtk2sp78&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Runner&lt;/a&gt;, the delivery usually took around two hours after the order was placed. To get your first order, you have to show your ID for them to make sure that you are over 19 years old. The delivery person from Runner was literally the only person we saw during 14 days of quarantine. After they confirm your ID, they would just leave a package by the door, knock and leave for every other delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We ordered twelve bottles of beer and two bottles of wine for our first delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Item total&lt;/strong&gt; $86.58&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivery Fee $9.99&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tax $4.24&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tip $5.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt; 103.87&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-deliveries&#34;&gt;Other deliveries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sure everyone knows about weed legalization in Canada. We were exhausted and devastated because of our situation, so we could not help but take advantage of it. Most of the deliveries need you to stop by the shop to show your ID, but some of them accept ID&amp;rsquo;s during the first delivery, for example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ocs.ca/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;OCS&lt;/a&gt; (looks like we saw two people during our quarantine, from Runners and OCS). Delivery was not so fast; it took them 2-3 days. We ordered a PAX vaporizer and some pods with a high level of CBD extracts to finally relax and get some sleep. The PAX costs $46.50, one pod costs around $50 on average (but it will last for half a year).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subtotal $96.45, including $11.00 tax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivery Fee $0.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, of course, Amazon. Amazon.ca is not as great as amazon.com, but you can still order almost anything with a fast delivery. For example, cleaning supplies. I subscribed to Amazon Prime to have 1-day delivery, which is also free for the first month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we were really missing during the quarantine was the PlayStation! We sold ours just before the trip in order to buy a new one here after the arrival. But again, we couldn&amp;rsquo;t do it because we were not sure if they let us stay here..and to be honest, where can you order PlayStation 5?! They are still not available anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, quarantine is a great time to read about everything that you need to get done after it ends (banks, contracts for mobile providers, renting an apartment), but to be honest, we didn&amp;rsquo;t research much since we were under terrible stress. Once a day, we went out to the balcony to &amp;ldquo;walk,&amp;rdquo; several times a week, we worked out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, you can survive 14 days quarantine, but it&amp;rsquo;s pretty easy to get mad. Perhaps the most unusual feeling is the understanding that you have been in a completely new country and a city for two weeks but have not yet seen anything except the view from your window. I really appreciated people who walked the dogs; I usually spent a few hours a day looking at them 🐶.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S. We paid for everything using our Russian &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tinkoff.ru/sl/7WyfhoLwreO&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Tinkoff bank&lt;/a&gt;, which lets you have a CAD balance on your card. Once the quarantine was over, our spending on groceries got less since we were not obligated to order everything, and thus we could spend less on delivery fees. Also, take outs usually give you great discounts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Story About One Almost Successful Relocation</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.com/posts/hello-canada/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 21:19:57 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.com/posts/hello-canada/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello, my name is Natasha, and I&amp;rsquo;m a person who plans everything, but nothing goes according to my plan because of very different circumstances (and then I suffer and get depressed). I always wanted to move from Russia. I had plenty of ideas, thoughts, and sometimes opportunities to do that, but it never really happened until this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Immigration and relocation is not an easy process, especially during a pandemic. I am sure that many of those who relocated have 1001 stories about how they moved, but ours is just very weird and unusual. I don&amp;rsquo;t even know where to start because I can&amp;rsquo;t share one part of this story (although it deserves special attention), so I&amp;rsquo;ll start somewhere in the middle but will capture the background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in April 2019, I started planning a relocation to Amsterdam with the company I worked in (a huge and pretty popular tech company). From that time, I lived in the &amp;ldquo;waiting mode&amp;rdquo; (I decided not to buy an apartment, didn&amp;rsquo;t rent a new apartment, and so on). Although the relocation paperwork process has not yet been launched, there have already been some agreements. In the fall of 2019, my husband and I even went to Amsterdam to check it out once again, talk to my uncle, who has been living there for more than 20 years, reviewed everything related to health insurance and what&amp;rsquo;s not.
And then a lot of things happened that did not depend on me, and I never went to Amsterdam. In fact, as I wrote at the beginning, I have been living in this &amp;ldquo;waiting mode&amp;rdquo; almost my whole life. I was always almost moving somewhere, but things happened in the last moments, and I didn&amp;rsquo;t move. I was very tired of living in this feeling, I really wanted to move, and I had the opportunity to go to Canada with my husband&amp;rsquo;s (D.) work. And now the story begins!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We managed to get our visas right before COVID happened and a few weeks before they started to close all the borders. So we got stuck in Russia with valid work visas. In general, even then, although it caused my emotional disbalance and regular tears, it gave me the hope that while we were waiting, something might change, and we could still move to Amsterdam. While the borders were closed, D. decided to change his last name. He wanted to do it for a long time; he had his reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, before even starting to apply for a new last name, we consulted with the immigration lawyers who handled the entire moving process. They said that he could go ahead and change his last name; there should be no issues since The USA and Canada usually allow people to enter the country with a valid visa even if it has an old last name. The main thing is that it is still the same person. While the process of changing the last name was in progress, Canada opened its borders and allowed it to enter the country for those who have work visas. When D. finally received all the new documents, he wrote an email to the lawyers to inform them that we were ready to fly. The first thing that surprised me was that the lawyers thought we had been in Canada for a long time already and that he was changing the last name inside the country.  Well, fine, in general, they told us again that everything was ok, but if we were too worried, we could write an email to the visa office to find out if they could re-issue the visa into a new passport. Unfortunately, the Visa Office said they would not do it, and if we want to get a new visa, we need to re-apply.
It took us a couple of weeks to get a visa before Covid happened, and now the process can take up to six months, so the lawyers advised us to travel with the current documents because, as they said in advance, there should be no issues at the border. The only ones who might have questions were the airline company, so the lawyers prepared a document that explained the situation to prevent any problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let&amp;rsquo;s skip everything that I felt when I quit (it was terribly difficult and took me an endless number of sleepless nights), goodbyes, accepting the fact that we were not moving to Europe, but to another continent (although I dreamed about it very much, but the older I got, the more I wanted to go to Europe. Also I had a lot of friends and relatives there, and would be close to my parents).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the scariest part before the trip was not to get Covid, because, in addition to the fact that the Covid itself was already very bad, it would also postpone the trip once again (we have been in the &amp;ldquo;waiting stage&amp;rdquo; for a year already). Okay, I will drop this part of the story again, although I must admit that my nervous system could not stand it all, and I had to start taking tranquilizers to live through it all. I calmed myself down; I hoped that we would move soon, arrive, and finally, I could just relax and come to my senses after all the hell that I have gone through this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On December 1, the moving company has packaged all of our belongings. They prepared two containers: one would travel by air (it would take two weeks to arrive in Canada), another one would travel by sea (it would take two months to arrive). There were two suitcases left for us with some necessary things that we would take on board. It is also worth mentioning that on December 1, we discovered that Canada requires additional confirmation for a person who travels as a family (me), which I didn&amp;rsquo;t have, of course. The lawyers assured us that since we received our visas before Covid, that rule didn&amp;rsquo;t concern me since I would be traveling using a work visa with an open work permit (and this is very important!). Well, sure, although at that moment, I just wanted to fall into a medical coma before I land on the other continent. But, oh well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;point-1---stpetersburg-pulkovo&#34;&gt;Point 1 - St.Petersburg, Pulkovo&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We arrived at Pulkovo, showed our documents, and of course, as we expected, there were problems with the last name. The issue was not related to the visa itself; the system did not allow to print the boarding pass. In 20 minutes and with the help of the &amp;ldquo;main&amp;rdquo; computer, they printed the tickets. They asked us whether we would be allowed to enter Canada with a different last name, we showed a letter from our lawyer, and they let us go. The border control also had no questions. They only asked me for a reason for my trip. I said that it was for work, and when asked where I worked, I said that I work in Toronto, and it worked:) I have an open work permit, I don&amp;rsquo;t have to have a job to enter the country, but it would be too complicated for Russian board control officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;point-2---istanbul&#34;&gt;Point 2 - Istanbul&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a 9-hour layover in Istanbul. My ex-colleagues told me about the hotel right at the airport, so we could get some sleep. After getting enough sleep, we went to get ready to &amp;ldquo;fight&amp;rdquo; with the local control services. Because Canada does not let everyone in, the control at the gate was pretty serious. We showed all the documents, but of course, there were questions about the last name change. The person who checked our documents took pictures of them and sent them to someone in What’s app. He said that he sent it to the Canadian Immigration Services. We were not sure though it was legal to take a picture of documents, including a job offer with the salary, and send them to someone unknown in What’s app. They asked me if I was traveling as a spouse; I said &amp;ldquo;no&amp;rdquo; because I had a work visa. But again, oh well, just let us on board! The plane was departing at 3:45 pm; at 3:40 pm, we still did not know whether they would let us on board. In the end, that man called the Canadian Immigration Service, who asked if D. was the same person or not. After confirmed it, they told him to let us on board immediately. Exactly at 3:45 pm, we got on the plane, the doors closed right behind us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we relaxed for a bit; the most exhausting part was behind us.
We only worried about one thing - what if the Border Control Officer asks me for supporting documents. Eleven hours of flight in N-95 masks (plus the time of the first flight and the transfer), a swollen nose, and we finally landed in Toronto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;point-3---toronto&#34;&gt;Point 3 - Toronto&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We landed in Toronto around 7 pm. The first officer looked at our documents and said that everything was ok, we could go-ahead to get our work permits. And then something happened that no one expected at all. We provided the Officer with our documents and explained the situation with the last name change. He listened, it looked like everything was clear. He just wanted to make sure that the job offer was still valid (after all, the job offer was almost a year old, and he had to make sure that the company was still waiting for D.). We showed him a confirmation, and he asked us to wait for a while. An hour and a half later, he returned to us saying that he reviewed our documents, but he couldn&amp;rsquo;t issue a work permit because he didn&amp;rsquo;t want to issue it with a new last name because all the documents have the previous last name. And he didn&amp;rsquo;t want to issue the work permit with an old last name because D. had a new last name. Of course, he couldn&amp;rsquo;t issue me a work permit because I&amp;rsquo;m a dependent. So he emailed the visa office and asked them what to do next. He told us to go to the apartments and stay on quarantine for 14 days (as planned) while he would be waiting for a reply from a visa office. He also took our passports and asked us to come back to the airport after the quarantine would be over, when he would tell us if they could re-issue a new work permit here in Canada or ask us to go back to Russia to re-apply for a new visa from scratch. Well, that sounded horrible! We called the lawyer, and he was also shocked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we quarantined for 14 days, we didn&amp;rsquo;t know our status here in Canada. We wouldn&amp;rsquo;t even order many groceries since we didn&amp;rsquo;t know if we would stay here or not. It was insane and mindblowing. I felt horrible; every day, I woke up with the thought: “Is this the last day in Canada? I haven&amp;rsquo;t even seen the city ”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On December 17, the quarantine was finally over, but there were still no news. The lawyer, as he said, did everything he could (but nothing happened). Just in case we need to go back to Russia, we decided to go and see Niagara right after the quarantine because we did not know if they would leave us here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On December 21, we went back to the airport. Our Officer was not there, and another Officer told us that our case was still in progress and that we should wait for another two weeks and come back on January 11 (which is three weeks!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we continue to live in this weird status, unable to work, open bank accounts, and rent an apartment. Our belongings cannot be sent here to Canada because The Russian customs service needs a photo of the stamp in the passport (and we do not have passports). In general, it isn&amp;rsquo;t easy to relax in this situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S. According to the lawyers&#39; plan, the Officer should have issued a work permit with an old last name by default, D. could start working here, and in the meantime, he would update the Work Permit.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>