<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Natasha&#39;s Journey</title>
    <link>https://natashakatson.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Natasha&#39;s Journey</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 19:22:13 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://natashakatson.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How Mat Leave Shaped Me as a Product Marketing Manager</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.com/posts/mat-leave/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 19:22:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.com/posts/mat-leave/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi everyone!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently started looking for a job after being off the market for two years. I was very scared to even start looking. I thought that in those two years, so many things happened that I missed! While I tried to keep up with the industry by checking LinkedIn even during my leave, I still felt quite bad about the whole thing and, honestly, about myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I thought, &amp;ldquo;I gave birth to a human being and survived the first few months; I don&amp;rsquo;t think anything can be more challenging than this,&amp;rdquo; and opened Notion to shape up a plan for my new project: &amp;ldquo;preparing for getting a job.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started thinking of all the projects I worked on, that&amp;rsquo;s when it clicked – mat leave wasn&amp;rsquo;t just a pause in my career, it was the most intense product marketing bootcamp ever. Now I get why parents constantly make these work-life comparisons and endless posts on LinkedIn. I spent my whole career swimming confidently through tech waters, then suddenly got dropped into parenthood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And let me tell you – despite what Instagram influencers suggest, none of this came naturally. It&amp;rsquo;s been the hardest job I&amp;rsquo;ve ever had, especially on days when sleep felt like a distant memory (so for the first 6 months at least). So here&amp;rsquo;s yet another post about how parenting can shape you professionally. By the way, as I am writing these lines my toddler is screaming &amp;ldquo;mama mama&amp;rdquo; because grandma wouldn&amp;rsquo;t let him do anything dangerous like drinking a soap. Talk about working under pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pre-launch-planning-preparing-for-birth&#34;&gt;Pre-Launch Planning: Preparing for Birth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like any good GTM, there&amp;rsquo;s a deadline, but it&amp;rsquo;s flexible and uncertain. You need to ship, but the timeline might shift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re running research sprints on birthing options, feeding methods, safe sleep, CPR, trying to validate sources, understand risks, and choose the best path forward. Just like any launch, there are cross-functional dependencies (midwives, nurses, doctors, a partner). You&amp;rsquo;re identifying blockers and gathering requirements with imperfect data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You also need to procure tools and systems (hello understanding what kind of clothes are for what), and build a &amp;ldquo;go-to-market&amp;rdquo; plan for life post-birth with very little real-world testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;launch&#34;&gt;Launch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a product launch, you usually get a bonus, team celebration, and maybe even a few days off. After pushing out a baby? You get financially poorer (seriously, very thankful for the Employment Insurance in Canada but it barely covers anything), physically wrecked, and introduced to a level of sleep deprivation that would violate human rights conventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is post-launch fire drill mode: you&amp;rsquo;re responding to new input constantly, solving feeding issues at 3 am, and trying to figure out when exactly you can sleep if the little human being is constantly feeding, trying to onboard a brand-new user who has zero documentation and a lot of demands. You&amp;rsquo;re juggling conflicting advice (doctors say this, midwives say that) and making decisions without knowing whether they&amp;rsquo;ll work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;keeping-the-product-alive&#34;&gt;Keeping the Product Alive&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re doing continuous discovery: What does this cry mean? Is this sleep regression (what IS sleep regression)? What&amp;rsquo;s the right wake window?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re iterating, tracking everything (diapers, feeds, sleep), using multiple apps to gain insights, and adjusting strategies weekly if not daily. Then you THINK you figured out your product and everything changes (just like anything in the Tech World these days). And all of this while your body is recovering, your identity is shifting, and your sleep is essentially gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;cross-functional-collaboration&#34;&gt;Cross-functional collaboration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My partner is amazing, and we&amp;rsquo;re doing this together, but when both team members are operating on 4 hours of broken sleep, alignment is hard. We&amp;rsquo;ve had to practice radical communication. Quick stand-ups, making decisions fast and under pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;parallel-projects&#34;&gt;Parallel projects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re also running logistics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Managing childcare waitlists that don&amp;rsquo;t work (does anyone know of childcare spots in Kitsilano, Mount Pleasant, or surrounding areas?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Navigating government systems (visa applications for visiting family = multi-step bureaucracy)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exploring drop-in programs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building new communications with tons of other parents at these programs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this while your &amp;ldquo;available hours&amp;rdquo; decrease as the baby naps less. My time management skills are sharper than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;cognitive-load&#34;&gt;Cognitive load&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, there were moments I felt like my brain wasn&amp;rsquo;t working at full capacity. But I&amp;rsquo;ve come to realize, it&amp;rsquo;s the opposite. It&amp;rsquo;s operating at over capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ability to absorb, process, and act on new information quickly, with minimal context and zero prep time? That&amp;rsquo;s now my default setting. Writing this post, for example, I&amp;rsquo;m racing against an unpredictable nap window and it&amp;rsquo;s honestly the hardest deadline I&amp;rsquo;ve ever had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here I am, back in the job market. Am I &amp;ldquo;returning to work” or showing up with a new set of sharpened skills, battle-tested through the most intense, high-stakes project I&amp;rsquo;ve ever run? I wish I could use this project as an example during the interviews along with my work-related projects but noone wants to hear about parenting because it&amp;rsquo;s not relevant (but it is!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually decided to write this post after a recent interview (for a role I&amp;rsquo;m very excited about) when they asked if I&amp;rsquo;m comfortable entering a new market and absorbing information quickly. That question made me realize how much my parenting experience has prepared me for exactly these challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, I find the job search to be a VERY hard project. Doing it after a break is even harder because of how you feel about yourself and because you have to remember details about projects you long ago forgot about. But I really hope that those who are hiring can understand: parental leave does not make you worse at your job. If anything, it makes you better. It&amp;rsquo;s a very hard project and you never know what comes next!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish I ended this post by saying &amp;ldquo;and look at me landing a job at a &lt;em&gt;company name&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;. But nope, it&amp;rsquo;s just the beginning of the journey and I have no idea how well it goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yeah, if you&amp;rsquo;re hiring or know someone who is, I would love to connect!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S. This isn&amp;rsquo;t to say that non-parents are worse at their jobs. It&amp;rsquo;s just to say: parental leave made me better at what I do (but also made me very exhausted lol).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hola, amigo! Vacation in Mexico, not all-inclusive</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.com/posts/vacation-in-mexico/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 10:00:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.com/posts/vacation-in-mexico/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We just got back from our trip to Mexico, and as per tradition, I’m writing a post about how we spent our time there and how much it all cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-mexico&#34;&gt;Why Mexico&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always had mixed feelings about choosing Mexico as a vacation destination. Most people go there for all-inclusive resorts, and we&amp;rsquo;re not really into that. A big part of our vacations is exploring nature, but I was always told that it&amp;rsquo;s unsafe to rent a car in Mexico and drive around on your own. Because of that, we always avoided going there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally, we planned to go to Thailand to meet up with family, but that didn’t work out, so we had to pick a closer destination. But we really wanted a warm tropical vacation with a warm sea!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There aren’t that many direct flights from Vancouver to such places; basically, it&amp;rsquo;s either Hawaii (USA) or Cancún (Mexico). There’s also Mexico’s western coast, but that&amp;rsquo;s the Pacific Ocean, which isn’t that warm in that area—it’s nothing like the Caribbean Sea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hawaii, as usual, turned out to be very expensive in terms of accommodations. But after asking around, including Mexican friends, we realized that renting a car in Mexico isn’t as scary as it seems. At some point, I opened Airbnb for Playa del Carmen (not far from Cancún), and for the same price that would get us a questionable one-bedroom place in Hawaii, we could rent a two-bedroom apartment with an amazing ocean view and a great location. So, we chose Mexico! I can’t say it was a super cheap vacation, but it wasn’t more expensive than our 2021 trip to Banff, and it was slightly more expensive than Hawaii.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;choosing-the-location&#34;&gt;Choosing the Location&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was probably the easiest step. Cancún is mostly full of all-inclusive hotels, so we ruled it out immediately. Tulum seemed beautiful, but after reading Reddit, I realized that it’s full of tourist scams and is generally very expensive. Playa del Carmen turned out to be the perfect middle ground, plus we got tons of recommendations from friends who had vacationed there a couple of times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We ruled out Mexico’s west coast due to the cold ocean. We really wanted to swim in warm water and hoped that Sam would finally start to enjoy being in the water, haha.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;flights&#34;&gt;Flights&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, we got sick a couple of weeks before the trip, but we were sure we’d recover in time. In the end, we flew while still half-sick, and I got hit with an awful pain that started in my nose, ran through my eye, and down to my teeth. Advil didn’t help, so D. ran around the plane looking for Tylenol. No one had any. After 30 minutes of searching, a kind woman asked if I was looking for medicine for a child. When D. said no, that the mom had a terrible headache, she offered some T3 tablets—Tylenol with caffeine and codeine (which is actually an opioid painkiller). Oh, those pre-Sam days when I thought I’d never take such strong painkillers, hahaha. Two pills later, I felt better, though later I did have a bit of a mental crisis about taking them, haha.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flight cost&lt;/strong&gt;: $779 CAD per person, so $1,550 CAD for two (kids under two fly for free).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a direct flight from Vancouver to Cancun during a popular season. We arrived on a Monday evening. Reddit warns about long passport control lines in Mexico, but we got through in about 10 minutes. There’s no priority line for families with kids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting to and from the airport in Vancouver&lt;/strong&gt;: $80 CAD. This time, we used Yellow Cab, which costs the same as Uber but is guaranteed to show up if booked in advance. Our flight was early in the morning, so we had to leave at 5 AM. In Vancouver, Yellow Cab has a fixed price for airport trips. We could have taken the SkyTrain, but it doesn’t go to Kitsilano, and dragging ourselves (and a toddler) to the train and then taking a bus at 5 AM didn’t seem fun. On the way back, we landed at 11 PM, so again, not the best time for public transport.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;accommodation&#34;&gt;Accommodation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost&lt;/strong&gt;: $3,238 CAD for 9 nights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We splurged on this one, haha. We could have rented a cheaper one-bedroom, but I saw an amazing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.airbnb.ca/rooms/1041259037558321263&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;two-bedroom apartment&lt;/a&gt; with an insane ocean view in a perfect location—right on the edge of the tourist zone and close to different beaches. The price was the same as the tiny studio we once rented on Vancouver Island, so we decided to go for it. Since I was comparing it to Hawaii at the time, it actually seemed very reasonable for such high quality, so I didn’t think twice (though maybe I should have, lol).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Sam had the worst luck—his crib looked very old and uncomfortable. But he handled it like a champ, so huge thanks to him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://natashakatson.com/images/mexico/airbnb.jpeg&#34;
         alt=&#34;The view&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The view&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;food&#34;&gt;Food&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We mostly ate at small local cafes—something in between touristy and authentic. The food was delicious, varied, and reasonably priced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://natashakatson.com/images/mexico/food.jpeg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Food&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Food&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Americans, though, have completely spoiled the locals when it comes to tipping. In some places, they would literally shove the payment terminal in our faces with a tipping screen already set up. But if it was a small family-run place, they didn’t do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Touristy restaurants were at least twice as expensive. We ate at one restaurant in the tourist zone once—it was beautifully decorated like a jungle, but the food was mediocre, and we paid twice as much as usual for a smaller portion.
Our usual meals were tacos, burritos, grilled chicken with vegetables, and fresh fruit smoothies. We had breakfast at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On average:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lunch average cost: 300 MXN ($20 CAD)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dinner average cost: 450 MXN ($31 CAD)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fresh coconuts: 35 MXN ($2.40 CAD) each—we drank them daily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total food costs&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Groceries (including diapers for Sam &amp;amp; beer for us): $257 CAD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eating out: $712 CAD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;language&#34;&gt;Language&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost no one spoke English, so we had to rely on hand gestures and broken Spanish. By the end of the trip, we actually learned a few words, haha. Mexicans reminded me of Russians who don’t speak English: they assumed that if you just spoke loudly and slowly in Spanish, non-Spanish speakers would magically understand. Somehow, I did manage to understand some things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;activities&#34;&gt;Activities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;beaches&#34;&gt;Beaches&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every morning, we went to the sea to a super nice little &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Playa&amp;#43;88/@20.6449546,-87.0578765,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m6!3m5!1s0x8f4e5dd5f9ba2c5f:0x7f12cfa43093ad5!8m2!3d20.6449546!4d-87.0553016!16s%2Fg%2F11nnzh404g?entry=ttu&amp;amp;g_ep=EgoyMDI1MDIwNS4xIKXMDSoASAFQAw%3D%3D&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;beach&lt;/a&gt;. This beach was a 20-minute walk from our home, but we liked it because it had showers, a toilet, free stationary umbrellas, and the beach itself was clean. In general, all the beaches were constantly cleaned of seaweed, so that wasn’t an issue. On weekends, this beach was hugely popular among locals, who love blasting Bluetooth speakers with all sorts of local and not-so-local pop music (which drives me crazy!). I usually went up to them and showed a ChatGPT-translated text asking them to lower the volume or turn it off. In general, people agreed, but the only problem was that behind me was always Sam, dancing, haha. It’s hard to ask people to turn down the music so we could enjoy the sound of the waves when our child is in the background dancing and vibing to their music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://natashakatson.com/images/mexico/beach.jpeg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Beach&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Beach&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The staff at this beach was funny; they all had a strong security-guard mentality, especially one woman. She always made sure not a single extra drop of water was spilled in the showers. Once, when Sam was playing with the water while I was trying to rinse my feet, she immediately ran up and asked me to turn off the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This beach also had an accessible wooden walkway so that people in wheelchairs and with strollers could get a little closer to the sea without walking through the sand. But this walkway was regularly cleaned of sand and then closed off so that no one would walk on it and spread sand around (on a beach, lol), even people with strollers—like us! Once, I asked them to open the walkway, but they pointed to a sign that said it was for people with disabilities only! And we, with our stroller and baby, could easily walk through the sand. Generally, we found this whole situation hilarious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other beaches were also clean, but they were much more crowded (since they were closer to the tourist zone) and didn’t have showers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cenotes&#34;&gt;Cenotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cenotes are small karst lakes, often turquoise in color, mostly found in caves. They form when the ground collapses over an underground river, making it slightly less underground. There are a lot of cenotes in this region, and I had dreamed of visiting one for a long time. They are indeed beautiful, but what we didn’t like is that it’s an incredibly commercialized attraction. Every cenote is a privately owned piece of land that charges an entrance fee (starting at 150 MXN and going up infinitely—we saw prices as high as 1,500 MXN). Because these are small plots of land, there’s no real hiking or jungle exploring, which we love. Basically, you arrive, pay for entry, swim/look around, leave, and go to another cenote, pay again, and repeat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://natashakatson.com/images/mexico/cenote.jpeg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Cenote&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Cenote&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If instead of this setup, there were national parks—even paid ones—where you could pay once and spend the whole day, it would have been much nicer and more interesting. That’s how we explored the jungles in Belize, Thailand, and Hawaii.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, as always, Americans have ruined even cenotes with their tipping culture. Tips are expected everywhere, even for visiting nature, so locals now expect tips from everyone. For example, in one cenote, we swam through a cave with a guide for four minutes. Another group, consisting of American women, immediately started discussing whether to tip $10 or $20 per person after exiting the water. For four minutes of swimming in an already paid-for cenote!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yeah, cenotes are pretty, but they aren’t worth the money, at least those small ones. And there’s basically nowhere to hike in the jungle in this region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, there is something resembling a giant park, run by the company Xcaret— the one with everything branded with &amp;ldquo;X&amp;rdquo;. But it&amp;rsquo;s more of a Disneyland-style network than a national park. It’s the most Americanized type of tourism, words can’t describe it. Just driving past, seeing a dozen of their hotels around cenotes and water parks, plus their ads literally every hundred meters along the Cancun-Playa highway, was enough to keep us away from any of their parks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In total&lt;/strong&gt;, we spent $101 CAD on the four cenotes we visited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;mayan-pyramids&#34;&gt;Mayan Pyramids&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of people go to see the Mayan pyramids. We decided to skip them this time because we had already seen many in Belize, and walking around in the heat with a toddler didn’t seem appealing. Also, it was nice to listen to and read about the history in English-speaking Belize, and we weren’t too eager to decipher signs in Spanish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;car-rental&#34;&gt;Car Rental&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone warned me against renting a car in Mexico: police demand bribes, roads are bad, and drivers are reckless. If you were born and raised in the U.S. or Canada, that might sound scary. But do you think that would scare someone who grew up in the post-Soviet world? 😆&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We decided that a car was necessary to explore the area. Plus, my Irish friend had just returned from vacation and recommended a local car rental company called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.localiza.com/mexico/es-mx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Localiza&lt;/a&gt;, we had a great experience with them. In the end, no one stopped us, but yeah, the driving is a bit chaotic. Still, no worse than in Belize, Thailand, or some parts of Russia, lol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Final costs&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gas: $60 CAD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rental: $387 CAD, including mandatory third-party liability insurance. We had our own insurance through a credit card.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-expenses&#34;&gt;Other Expenses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time, instead of &lt;a href=&#34;https://ref.airalo.com/fVur&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Airalo&lt;/a&gt;, we tried a new app, MobiMatter (promocode NATYX37204). The rates were slightly cheaper. I constantly used Google Maps, which eats up data like crazy. Plus, the Airbnb had crappy Wi-Fi, so I had to use mobile data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total cost&lt;/strong&gt; for mobile service: $51 CAD for both of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We mostly paid with a credit card. Yes, there was a small transaction fee from the bank, but overall, it was still the best option. We withdrew cash a couple of times from an ATM with a $5 CAD fee. Withdrawing local currency from an ATM is cheaper than bringing cash and exchanging it at currency exchange offices. The key is to decline the ATM’s currency conversion offer because their rate is 15-20% worse than the market rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, in Mexico, almost everything can be bought over the counter at a pharmacy. We flew out while feeling a bit sick, and after the flight, I developed an ear infection. I immediately bought the drops that usually help me. We also bought a few other things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total pharmacy expenses&lt;/strong&gt;: $50 CAD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;traveling-with-a-toddler&#34;&gt;Traveling with a Toddler&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haha, traveling with a toddler is a unique kind of fun. Though at 15 months, maybe he’s not a full-fledged toddler yet, but he’s getting there fast. Our son is generally very active and incredibly social. The flight there was six hours, and he napped for just one of them. The rest of the time, he ran up and down the plane, waving at everyone. We were already exhausted from the airport since he kept running away from us everywhere, so by the time we got on the plane, we were completely drained, lol. But overall, it wasn’t too bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as the vacation itself, I think it went as well as it could. Sam absolutely loved the sand and was hugging everyone on the beach. He probably hugged around ten strangers a day. Mexicans seem to really love kids—teenagers, men, women, everyone played with him, shared their toys, etc. So, our super social child was happy, and we were at peace. There were no issues with food in Mexico—chicken is everywhere, and he loves it. For example, my friend struggled a bit with her kid on a trip to Maui, Hawaii, because most of the food there is raw fish (poke), and it was hard to find meals for a toddler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, we really missed having some downtime. The only time we got to relax was when he was sleeping, just like at home. The first few days, we couldn’t understand why we even thought it was a good idea to go on vacation without grandma, haha. At one point, we saw our neighbors arrive with two kids and TWO grandmas—now that’s proper vacation planning! But after a couple of days, we got used to it, fell into some kind of routine, and it didn’t feel as hard. Plus, he fell in love with the sea and the sand, as well as the stroller, which he usually refuses to sit in at home, so we could actually go for walks. The only downside—he wanted to go out for a walk as soon as he woke up at 6, sometimes even at 5 AM. But at some point, you just get used to the constant screaming—it turns into a kind of white noise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people told us that there’s no point in spending money on a vacation because traveling with a baby or a toddler isn’t really a vacation. But I wouldn’t say that’s true. It’s an amazing change of scenery, which I personally REALLY needed. And it’s still nice to swim, explore, and see new places, even if relaxing physically is nearly impossible with a little human attached to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flight back was tougher. Not so much the flight itself but the waiting beforehand. We decided to go into the business lounge since we had access, and Sam immediately started destroying everything and bothering everyone. We couldn’t sit still for a second. The people in the lounge were so uptight, as if they hadn’t just been on vacation! Almost no one waved back at him, and he got sad. The only exception was a small group of African American guys who were super positive and played along with him—huge respect to them! But D. and I were so exhausted that we downed five margaritas between the two of us, haha. The first three hours of the flight, he was running up and down the plane again, but then he finally crashed for the night, and life got easier. 😀&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://natashakatson.com/images/mexico/business_lounge.jpeg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Drinking margarita at a business lounge&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Drinking margarita at a business lounge&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total cost of the trip&lt;/strong&gt;: $6666 CAD. A devilish vacation, haha.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts-on-mexico&#34;&gt;Thoughts on Mexico&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t speak for all of Mexico—it’s a huge country—but overall, I really enjoyed vacationing in Playa del Carmen at this stage of life. If it weren’t for the lack of hiking options in the jungle, it would’ve been perfect! The Caribbean Sea is unbelievably warm, and swimming in it is pure joy. We felt very safe—honestly, I’d say safer than in downtown Vancouver. The locals are friendly as long as you’re not in super touristy areas (there, they’re really pushy about selling stuff, which I don’t like). Americans have definitely ruined the region, but oh well—people say the same thing about Russians in Thailand, lol. Renting a car isn’t scary, the food is delicious and affordable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I really want to go to Mexico City and see a more authentic side of Mexico—its architecture and culture. I’m also really glad we didn’t do an all-inclusive (which, by the way, we couldn’t find cheaper than $6-7k for some reason). Staying in one room with a toddler, eating hotel food, and hanging around the same pool all day? No, thank you.
Overall, I loved the trip, and I already want to go back to the ocean!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://natashakatson.com/images/mexico/palm.jpeg&#34;
         alt=&#34;a palm&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;a palm&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How am I - October</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.com/posts/how-am-i-fall/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2024 10:00:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.com/posts/how-am-i-fall/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone! It’s been a while since I’ve posted a &amp;ldquo;how am I&amp;rdquo; update.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll start by saying that the fall has arrived, in case you haven’t noticed. The leaves are yellow, and the mood is a bit grey. Though, fall is now much brighter than it used to be because Sam (our son) has his birthday in November. Aside from that, a pile of tasks and worries has come crashing down on me again. It’s worth noting that I can only deal with all of this during the baby’s nap time, so I have about two hours a day for everything, and I still need to fit in cooking and some cleaning during that time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though D. helps a lot, he’s still working, so I’m quite exhausted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-landlord&#34;&gt;The Landlord&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our landlord never ceases to surprise us! Like most apartments in Vancouver, the heating in the living room is provided by a gas fireplace. For safety reasons, the fireplace needs to be serviced once a year—it’s gas, after all. Our management company (the strata) collaborates once a year with a company that services these fireplaces. It costs $110 after tax if you use their services when they’re servicing our building, and $170 if it’s done at a different time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We saw a notice in the elevator and decided to email our landlord to request servicing the fireplace, as it hasn’t been serviced once during our time living here. We also learned from the building manager that last year someone had a gas leak, which was discovered during routine servicing, and a dog even got sick because of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually if something needs fixing, she sends her father to do the repairs. D. even suggested hiring a company ourselves and servicing the fireplace at our expense, but I refused and wrote her a friendly email: explaining the safety concerns and the fact that the fireplace makes a horrible noise when heating (which is true).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s when it started! She said her father would come and take a look at the fireplace. What followed was a long email exchange, where I explained that only a licensed technician can inspect a gas fireplace (I even found an article about it), that we could be breathing in gas, and that she could be held responsible for it. I suggested we simply hire a company. But she either ignored me or continued saying her father would come to check it himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, even if he comes, I won’t let him near the fireplace. I even called the BC Tenancy Board to find out who’s right in this situation. They told me we can hire a company ourselves and then file a complaint, after which she’ll be required to refund the $110.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly, my mind is blown by the fact that she’s making such a fuss over $110. Our rent is $3622 a month, and she doesn’t even have a mortgage as far as I know! Plus, we suspect she hasn’t serviced the fireplace in the 15 years she’s owned the apartment, because it seems like she doesn’t even understand what we’re talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;daycares&#34;&gt;Daycares&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sam will soon be a year old, and he’s an incredibly social child who always wants to be around other kids. I try to take him to different children’s programs in the area, but, of course, I’d love to get him into daycare. Plus, I’m ready to get back into work mode and think about something other than sleep, food, and taking care of a little human.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the daycare situation in Vancouver is super sad. You apparently can’t get on waitlists while pregnant (which is a good thing I think), so I signed up when he was a couple of months old (right after birth, I physically couldn’t deal with it). We’re on about 15 waiting lists, and things aren’t looking great. People say waitlists don’t matter as much, and you just have to keep calling and hope you get lucky. I started doing that a few weeks ago, but no luck so far, and it seems like daycare isn’t in our near future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people hire a nanny shared between two families, but if daycare costs $1700-2000, a nanny costs around $4000, which is extremely expensive. Meanwhile, in North Vancouver, Burnaby, Coquitlam, and Richmond (cities outside Vancouver), the daycare situation is better, but it’s too far for us. All of this is really frustrating and demotivating. Not to mention how much energy it takes to deal with it all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;frozen-money&#34;&gt;Frozen Money&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our money has been frozen since 2022, CBC wrote about it &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/canada-russia-ukraine-sanctions-1.6736088&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It’s now October 2024, and nothing has changed. I send emails weekly. Over this time, I’ve contacted numerous officials: sent requests to Global Affairs to unblock the funds, wrote to Mélanie Joly as both an MP and as a minister (different emails), our MP (she’s told by Global Affairs that they’re “working on it”), the Premier of British Columbia (they responded saying that there are upcoming elections and they don’t have time), the BC Minister of Finance (no response), MPs in Toronto when we still lived there, and of course to CBC when they were doing a series of TV, radio, and online stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of that, I wrote to the host of This Hour Has 22 Minutes because he has a lot of connections (no reply). I wrote to Ilya Kolmanovsky (a Russian science journalist and podcaster) because I thought he might have some connections. He was very kind and gave me contacts, but it didn’t help. I’m in touch with other people in the same situation, and nothing is working. We still can’t get our money unfrozen, and no one seems to care. Of course, I send follow-up requests to Global Affairs once a month, but they’re ignored as well. I don’t know where else to turn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;on-other-things&#34;&gt;On other things&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m really annoyed that Amazon is forcing everyone to return to the office five days a week! It’s setting a bad example for the industry. I’m dreaming of finding a remote job because I can’t imagine how both of us could work in an office and still manage things with a baby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Motherhood is not easy. On the one hand, I’m incredibly happy every morning to see this little person, we’ve got his sleep under control, and my dream of uninterrupted sleep has come true (probably temporary). On the other hand, I’m exhausted mentally and physically. I think the hardest part of all of this is the lack of breaks. At work, when you’re tired, you know the weekend is coming, and you’ll be able to sleep in, switch off, and recharge. In parenting, Saturday isn’t much different from Friday, except I’ve started a small tradition of going to a coffee place on Saturday mornings to enjoy some coffee alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, we’ve become really close with our neighbors who have kids, and we try to take turns babysitting in the evenings if someone wants to go on a date. D. and I really need to get out soon. The problem is that by the evening, I’m so tired that all I want to do is sleep. I have to admit, before motherhood, I didn’t know what real exhaustion was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, the Perinatal Mental Health program from BC Women’s is ending soon, which makes me sad because I really enjoy talking to the psychiatrist from the program. Recently, I found out that they also have sleep specialists, and they were incredibly helpful too. Speaking of motherhood and the fact that Sam will be a year old soon—guess if I’ve made it to the OBGYN? Nope, still haven’t. I haven’t made it anywhere because the wait times are insane here. It’s honestly ridiculous, to say the least.
In July, I went on a two-day trip alone to Calgary to visit a friend, and it really helped me unwind. Looks like I’ll need to do that again :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m, of course, really happy that D. and I have an equal partnership when it comes to parenting, but I have to admit that a lot more responsibility still falls on women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://natashakatson.com/images/how-am-I-fall/Sam_at_the_library.jpeg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Sam at the library&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Sam at the library&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Postpartum care in Canada</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.com/posts/postpartum/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 10:00:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.com/posts/postpartum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone!
I wrote this post about five months ago, but never got around to finishing and publishing it. The time has come! I’ll share my experience with postpartum care for both the child and the mother here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn’t know much about children at all, so I had a hard time imagining how to learn everything and where to get reliable information during those early days when you have no energy for anything (I don’t trust social media bloggers). But it turned out not to be so scary; there was support, especially in the beginning. I’ll talk about the specialists who monitor the child and mother in British Columbia, though it may differ slightly in other provinces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;midwife&#34;&gt;Midwife&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first 6 weeks after giving birth, we were under the care of our midwives. The first couple of months were quite tough. Besides the fact that the baby lost 11% of his weight (the norm is considered to be up to 10% weight loss), he was gaining weight very poorly, and everyone was trying to figure out why. The midwives were terribly worried about the baby&amp;rsquo;s poor weight gain and came to our home every other day for two weeks. Usually, as far as I know, they come a few times during the first week, and by the second week, they expect a clinic visit. They also advised us on what to do with feeding: for example, how to increase milk production, how and when to give formula, pump, what to use, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://natashakatson.com/images/postpartum/midwife.jpeg&#34;
         alt=&#34;The midwife weighing the baby&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The midwife weighing the baby&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first days, we called the midwife pager 24/7, asking everything from &amp;ldquo;what to do, he’s crying constantly&amp;rdquo; to questions about the color of poop, of course haha. We could even send a photo via text for assessment :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time they came to check on the baby, they also checked on me: examining how everything was healing, asking about my condition, and talking to us about how to better organize our lives so that each of us could get some sleep. For up to 4 weeks, I felt like we had constant support, but after that, when we were transferred to the pediatrician (more on that below) and the midwives got new babies to care for, they didn’t pay much attention to us. While the baby was still closely monitored during visits, my complaints were usually dismissed with &amp;ldquo;it’ll pass on its own,&amp;rdquo; and they didn’t even check. By the end of the 6 weeks, I felt like I was no longer of interest to them. At least, that’s how it felt compared to how attentive they were to me during pregnancy versus a month after giving birth. After 6 weeks, our care with the midwives ended; they handed me documents from the hospital discharge, showed me how to use a mirror to check how everything was healing (lol), and sent us on our way. From that moment, we entered the regular Canadian healthcare system, and it still disappoints me, especially in British Columbia!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;lactation-consultants&#34;&gt;Lactation Consultants&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lactation consultants assist with all questions related to feeding the baby, from breastfeeding to bottle feeding and other techniques to ensure the baby isn’t left hungry. For up to 6 weeks, lactation consultants are covered by government medical insurance if referred by a doctor or midwife. Without a referral, you can see a consultant for a fee, which costs around $130-160 CAD. We were referred to confirm that the baby had a tight tongue-tie and to determine how much milk was being consumed directly from the breast. This was a whole new world for me; I didn’t know such specialists existed. One downside is that you have to come to the appointment with a hungry baby, which often disrupted our schedule. Appointments with lactation consultants last about an hour and a half, and they don’t rush you. After 6 weeks, free appointments end. In general, most of our issues were more or less resolved by this time. However, if help was needed later on, there are also lactation doctors you can see for free (as our last lactation consultant mentioned) with a referral from a family doctor. Though their appointments aren’t as long. We visited a few lactation consultants, one clinic called Richmond Breastfeeding Centre (The Milk Maven) with Candace, who we didn’t like much, and another consultant at the South Community Birth Program, who we liked a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;family-doctor&#34;&gt;Family Doctor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 6 weeks of midwife care, the baby is referred to the family doctor for monitoring, if you have one. The family doctor can check the baby once a month, measuring length, weight, and head circumference, and also administer vaccinations according to the vaccination schedule. Any issues are addressed with the family doctor, though getting an appointment, as usual, is difficult. This is quite frightening because if something urgent but not emergency-worthy arises, there’s nowhere else to turn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pediatrician&#34;&gt;Pediatrician&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the birth, we suspected that the baby had a tight tongue-tie (which caused feeding and weight gain issues), but two of our midwives denied this. A couple of weeks later, a third midwife confirmed the problem and referred us to a lactation consultant (as mentioned above). In the fourth week, the weight gain completely stopped, so we were sent to a pediatrician. Here’s the interesting part: you can only see a pediatrician if there’s a problem. Routine check-ups are done by the family doctor. In the USA (and of course in post-Soviet countries), for example, pediatricians handle children’s care. Since a pediatrician is a specialist, I expected a long wait for the appointment, but it wasn’t bad—we only had to wait a week, which is an eternity in the life of a small child.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we saw the pediatrician, we could consult them without a referral for six months (this seems to apply to any specialist, as it turns out). The appointments weren’t rushed; they always answered all our questions and was very attentive. I often read on Reddit about how in the US, you can call your pediatrician with any question. We don’t have that luxury here. However, we were referred to the pediatrician again when the baby was 7 months old, so now we can consult with them on any child-related issue for the next six months, which is convenient!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the way, the tongue-tie was surprisingly cut by a dentist. We did it at Redtree Dental and were happy with the experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://natashakatson.com/images/postpartum/dentist.jpeg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Tongue-tie procedure&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Tongue-tie procedure&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;public-nurse&#34;&gt;Public Nurse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my post about pregnancy in Canada, I mentioned that during pregnancy, you can contact a public nurse. Google says a public nurse is a public health nurse who provides a wide range of healthcare services, including disease prevention and health promotion. During my pregnancy, I was connected with a public nurse who followed up after my discharge from the hospital and started communicating with me again every couple of weeks after the midwife’s care ended. You can ask them any questions related to the child’s health and development. Immunizations can be done at the center where they work, but we usually do them with our family doctor. Since it’s hard to get an appointment with the family doctor quickly, I usually call or text our public nurse with minor questions. I have her number and can even send them text messages if something is not urgent. She calls me every couple of weeks, and I can consult her on anything from &amp;ldquo;why hasn’t the baby pooped in three days&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;what should we do with him all day.&amp;rdquo; I find it very helpful to talk to her, even if I’m just complaining about something. It’s especially nice that she cares not only about the baby’s health but also about mine. A public nurse can be with you for up to five years! I really like her; she’s very responsive, kind, and caring. We’re very lucky with her. She recently changed her clinic but kept us as her clients because she said she likes us too. Thanks for that!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;physiotherapy&#34;&gt;Physiotherapy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From about three weeks old, we started going to physiotherapy to help the baby develop his tongue and mouth muscles after the tongue-tie procedure and to assist us with feeding issues. I really enjoyed our sessions, so even after we solved the main problems, we continued going to physiotherapy. They showed us exercises to do with the baby for development, etc. After each session, the physiotherapist sent us a list of exercises to do at home. Physiotherapy isn’t covered by government insurance but is covered by work insurance. I highly recommend &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kidsphysio.ca/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Kids Physio&lt;/a&gt;; they have many locations, and we went to the one on Cambie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://natashakatson.com/images/postpartum/physio.jpeg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Physiotherapy session&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Physiotherapy session&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mental-support&#34;&gt;Mental Support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my pregnancy, due to increased anxiety, I was seeing a psychiatrist from the &lt;a href=&#34;%28http://www.bcwomens.ca/our-services/mental-health-substance-use/reproductive-mental-health%29&#34;&gt;Reproductive Mental Health program at BC Women’s&lt;/a&gt;. After giving birth, care continues for up to a year. I speak with her every couple of months. You can contact her anytime for an appointment or a prescription. If you want to see her more frequently, you must make a case for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-specialists&#34;&gt;Other Specialists&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of January, after an examination, my family doctor referred me to a OBGYN because I was experiencing some issues. In April! I finally saw her, but the appointment lasted only five minutes, and it was terrible (so much so that I eventually decided to file an official complaint against her). She didn’t help me at all, so I was scheduled to see three other OBGYN. My child is now 9 months old, and I still haven’t seen any of them. To say I’m in shock is an understatement. Once again, I’ve been dealing with some postpartum concerns (they’re not as severe as they were before, but still present), and I haven’t been able to see a OBGYN in 9 months. Shocked? So am I. Yes, I’m on every cancellation list; it’s not my first day living in Canada :) My family doctor even personally called the clinic and requested that they see me, but nothing worked. My nurse also wrote some emails somewhere, but that didn’t help either. That’s how things stand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, to be honest, due to the inability to see a OBGYN, I’m left with the feeling that after giving birth, the system doesn&amp;rsquo;t care about women (where are the feminist organizations when they’re so needed?!). Even though the Government is willing to allocate resources for a women’s mental health, it seems like no one cares about their physical health, even though they are connected. Meanwhile, my experience with my child’s care has been relatively positive—we even managed to see a specialist in the hospital just a week after getting a referral (even the pediatrician was surprised). We’re currently waiting for some tests at the children’s hospital, but no one has called us yet. Surely, there are women with positive stories about getting healthcare after childbirth, but even my psychiatrist at BC Women’s Hospital wasn’t surprised by the long wait and said, unfortunately, the situation with healthcare is broken right now. That’s all I wanted to share today.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>We got Canadian PR!</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.com/posts/we-got-a-pr/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 10:00:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.com/posts/we-got-a-pr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone! It’s been a while since I last wrote, and that’s because having a little one at home makes maintaining a full-fledged blog quite difficult. Plus, there weren’t many updates to share. But today, I’m finally writing this post as a permanent resident of Canada!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, it finally happened—we got PR. I’m incredibly happy to write this post! Whee, just two more years and we can finally apply for citizenship. It’s been a nerve-wracking and laborious journey, and it&amp;rsquo;s scary to look back on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me try to summarize everything in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2019&#34;&gt;2019&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D. and I had just met, and my job at the time was opening an office in Amsterdam, where I was in line to relocate. Meanwhile, D. went through an interview process at Microsoft out of curiosity and unexpectedly received a job offer. Microsoft proposed a one-year move to Canada, after which we could apply for an L1 visa to move to Seattle, USA (though things didn’t go as planned, haha). We deliberated where to go, with our hearts set on Europe. However, my job faced many changes, and instead of relocating, I was told to wait a bit longer, so we slowly applied for a Canadian visa and received it in March 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2020&#34;&gt;2020&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My couple of months of waiting turned into several more months. Meanwhile, we were desperate to leave Russia, so we decided that a bird in the hand is worth two in the bush and chose to move to Canada. Then COVID hit, and all flights were canceled. During this time, D. changed his last name, and I kept trying to move to Amsterdam. However, since I was told to wait again, we packed our things and moved to Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon arrival, we were met by an extremely unfriendly officer who refused to issue us a work permit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2021&#34;&gt;2021&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We lived in Canada for one and a half months without status, under immense stress that we would be sent back. But finally, we received a one-year work permit instead of two years. We were incredibly happy. Throughout 2021, we made friends, which helped us integrate quickly and settle in. In spring 2021, we sent our diplomas for evaluation to register on the Express Entry portal for PR, just in case, and in summer, we scored excellently on the English test. Also, in summer 2021, we applied to renew our work permit, and in November of the same year, we received a letter from immigration stating that they couldn’t renew it because that first officer had given us a special status usually given to criminals, so the whole process had to start over and would take about a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2022&#34;&gt;2022&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our work permits were about to expire, and our lawyers recommended doing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.immigrationstationcanada.com/post/what-is-flagpoling&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;flagpoling&lt;/a&gt;. With the risk of not being allowed back in, we went to the Canada-US border, got refused entry into the US (it&amp;rsquo;s a part of the procedure), and returned to Canada. Luckily, the officers were kind, removed our special status, and issued a two-year work permit. Meanwhile, we prepared documents for the L1 visa and became eligible for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.canada.ca/en/immigration-refugees-citizenship/services/immigrate-canada/express-entry/eligibility/canadian-experience-class.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Canadian Experience Class&lt;/a&gt; draw, waiting to be selected for Canadian PR. You might ask, why did we need this if we were planning to go to the US? I’ll tell you. As immigrants who had already lost years of our lives due to stress over our status, we really wanted permanent status in Canada to breathe easily and return if things didn’t work out in the US. For instance, if we lost our jobs or were denied a US visa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In February 2022, Russia invaded Ukraine, making life with a Russian passport even more stressful. In March, we went on a long-planned vacation to Belize and got stuck there because the immigration service deactivated D.&amp;rsquo;s Canadian visa, which we found out at the airport check-in for our return flight to Canada. My nerves over our temporary status finally broke, and I anxiously checked every draw we couldn’t get into, freaking out each time they took 5 points away from me on my birthday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the fall of 2022, it turned out that Canada had stopped draws for the Canadian Experience Class for about a year, and when the program resumed, the scores were very high, and we didn’t qualify. Since Microsoft was preparing documents for the L1 visa, they refused to provide a certificate of one year of work, which would have given us 50 points in the Express Entry system, and we couldn’t get selected. Meanwhile, D. realized that working at Microsoft was not what he hoped for and interviewed at Apple. This time the conditions were similar: work in Canada for a year and then move to the US on an L1 visa, but first, we had to move to Vancouver. We went through the process of renewing the work permit, getting Canadian visas, and everything all over again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2023&#34;&gt;2023&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without a new work permit but with a letter from immigration saying we would eventually get it, we moved to Vancouver, and D. started his new job. We still couldn’t get into a draw (sometimes I was just two points short). In summer, our CELPIP results expired since they are valid for only two years, and we had to retake it. We retook it with excellent scores, even a bit higher than last time. But our Express Entry points were still insufficient: I had 494 points, D. had 484, and the draws required 500+ points. There were no separate draws for STEM or CEC with lower scores. In November 2023, we had a baby, and Apple allowed us to delay the relocation to the US for a few months. We realized that we had been in Canada for three years, all our friends were getting citizenship, and we were still constantly renewing our visas and work permits. The political situation in the world was, to put it mildly, not great, and we really wanted Canadian citizenship. Also, our money was and is still &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cbc.ca/news/politics/canada-russia-ukraine-sanctions-1.6736088&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;frozen&lt;/a&gt; in Canada, and if we left, our accounts would be closed, and the chance of getting our money would be almost zero. D. explained the situation at work, but they still refused to provide the certificate that would give us 50 points for the same reason as Microsoft. In December 2023, we finally got selected for the STEM draw and submitted our PR documents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2024&#34;&gt;2024&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D.’s manager didn’t mind if we stayed in Canada for a couple of years, but unfortunately, the team’s policy required him to be physically with the team, meaning moving to Seattle. We weighed all the pros and cons. The main argument was that although financially it would be much easier in the US, it would take at least 5-6 years to apply for citizenship, whereas in Canada, it would be two years after getting PR. After everything we had gone through with temporary documents, we really wanted to apply for a passport as soon as possible, so we decided to risk it and stay in Canada for now. D. went through interviews from scratch to switch to a local team (which was also hard to find!), he succeeded, and we stayed. Due to our convoluted work permit history and when we arrived in Canada (technically in December 2020, officially in January 2021), we were terribly worried that the PR process could take years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pr-timeline&#34;&gt;PR Timeline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the timeline turned out much more pleasant, albeit longer than for other acquaintances:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;December 8, 2023: Selected&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 8, 2024: Submitted documents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;May 7: Medical request. We emailed that we had already done the medical exam and that they accepted it under the new rules. IRCC confirmed this within a few days.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;May 17: Biometrics request&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;June 11: Request for D.&amp;rsquo;s military status in the country of origin. We were tense because the military ID didn’t have the new last name. We sent it for translation online, got the translation within a day, and submitted it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;June 18: Received the so-called P1 (first portal email), meaning—your PR is approved, confirm some personal information and that you are currently in Canada.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;July 11: Received the second email—P2, where we had to again confirm that we were in Canada and upload our address and photo for the PR card.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;July 15, 2024: eCoPR—Electronic Confirmation of Permanent Residence. The status confirmation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, just two more years and we can finally apply for citizenship! We are incredibly happy, but as our friend commented, “Why did it take so long? Our government is inherently flawed!” :) Next steps—celebrate with poutine, continue fighting to get our money back, and apply for citizenship in two years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://natashakatson.com/images/PR/PR.jpeg&#34;
         alt=&#34;maple leaf and I&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;maple leaf and I&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How We Rented A Condo in Toronto</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.com/posts/rent/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2021 19:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.com/posts/rent/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I&amp;rsquo;ll share my experience of looking for a condo (an apartment) in Toronto. A disclamer: I&amp;rsquo;ll refer to our condo as an apartment just because it sounds more familiar to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we have a temporary place till March 3, we have recently signed a lease to a new place, and we should get the keys on February 17. As a person who has recently moved here from Russia, I still feel that it&amp;rsquo;s all a fraud, but hopefully, this country is more civilized, and a signed lease gives you some guarantees. It&amp;rsquo;s a long read, but I really tried to explain in details how everything works here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-1---learn-about-the-city&#34;&gt;Step 1 - learn about the city&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few weeks before moving to Toronto, we decided to learn a little bit about its neighborhoods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, I emailed my friend who moved to Toronto 16 years ago (and we haven&amp;rsquo;t talked much since then). I asked him to divide the city into several zones, where red would show the areas that it&amp;rsquo;s better to avoid, and green would show friendly neighborhoods. And I got the following image from him.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://natashakatson.com/images/areas.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;areas&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then we found a &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/aCLEoLEzUZs&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; on YouTube about the five best neighborhoods in Toronto where a guy shared details about different areas and whether it&amp;rsquo;s possible to get there without a car. We added all the neighborhoods to Google maps to check them out later when we actually move to Toronto.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I asked about nice neighborhoods in a Russian &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.me/canada_it&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;channel&lt;/a&gt; on Telegram about the Tech industry in Canada. They recommended me the following areas: High Park, Humber Bay Shores, Mimico, Roncesvalles, Sunnyside. We also added those places to Google maps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-2---explore-the-neighborhoods&#34;&gt;Step 2 - explore the neighborhoods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we only got work permits after a month and a half of being in Canada, we had enough time to check out the city after the quarantine.
I was pretty disappointed with Toronto&amp;rsquo;s architecture; the city has many skyscrapers, most of them are high-rise condo-buildings, not even the offices. I once lived in a tall building in St.Petersburg, and I hated it. Of course, condo-buildings here are different: they have a swimming pool, a gym, a concierge service, but living in a high-rise building is rarely a pleasure (at least that&amp;rsquo;s how I feel).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another essential thing to us was transport accessibility. Like the USA, Canada is a country built for cars, but Toronto is partially covered by the subway. We would gladly buy a car and rent a house somewhere outside of the city, but our license here in Ontario is only valid for the first two months after arrival, and due to COVID-19, driving exams have been canceled. Even when the offices reopen, the queues there are already for six months ahead. Therefore, it was important for us to choose an area so we can comfortably live there without a car.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After we got out of quarantine, we went to explore the areas. At first, we took the subway, but then we realized that it was not a productive way to explore the city. Therefore, we decided to rent a car for a day and go around all the previously marked areas in Google maps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very first area that we saw was &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/High&amp;#43;Park/@43.641955,-79.4554729,14.03z/data=!4m5!3m4!1s0x882b35d32336f705:0x1bcc825a300ee67!8m2!3d43.6465479!4d-79.4636903&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;High Park&lt;/a&gt; and everything around it. I really liked it there: low houses, a huge park, shops, restaurants, bars, a subway line. I won&amp;rsquo;t say that the area is close to the downtown, it&amp;rsquo;s about half an hour away from it. And it is unlikely that we will need to go to downtown a lot with offices being closed and everything. Other areas were not that great: some of them had mostly old houses, which we could not rent anyway because it makes no sense and it&amp;rsquo;s too expensive to rent a whole house for two of us; others only had high-rise buildings (for example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps?q=humber&amp;#43;bay&amp;amp;um=1&amp;amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwj8ntSI9c7uAhUGElkFHdqbDSsQ_AUoAXoECBcQAw&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Humber Bay Shore&lt;/a&gt;); some areas were cozy but difficult to get to without a car (for example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Long&amp;#43;Branch,&amp;#43;Toronto,&amp;#43;ON/@43.5912977,-79.5425108,15z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x882b484122f10ee1:0x18d94d109b9f2dc8!8m2!3d43.593421!4d-79.538164&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Long Branch&lt;/a&gt;). As for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Mississauga,&amp;#43;ON/@43.5772409,-79.6344311,11z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x882b469fe76b05b7:0x3146cbed75966db!8m2!3d43.5890452!4d-79.6441198&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mississauga&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Oakville,&amp;#43;ON/@43.466272,-79.8334236,11z/data=!4m5!3m4!1s0x882b5b8b8f729979:0x5037b28c7231bd0!8m2!3d43.467517!4d-79.6876659&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Oakville&lt;/a&gt;, these are two very nice towns that are located close to Toronto but it seemed inconvenient to live there without a car, even though the variety of places for rent there is huge and housing is cheaper than in the city.
My favorite neighborhood was &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Bridle&amp;#43;Path,&amp;#43;Toronto,&amp;#43;ON/@43.7340798,-79.3768215,15z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x89d4cd39eae61e4b:0xf462ffb9f7f22860!8m2!3d43.7359137!4d-79.3718986&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bridle Path&lt;/a&gt;, but we wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be able to rent anything there 🥲. Various celebrities live in that area, for example, Drake (and his house is worth about $100 million CAD). We didn&amp;rsquo;t consider renting a place in downtown because although all the offices, the lake, and other entertainment places are located there, there are still too many homeless people, high-rise buildings, and it&amp;rsquo;s generally uncomfortable to live there if you ask me. After all, downtown in North America and Europe differs a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-3---learn-about-different-types-of-housing&#34;&gt;Step 3 - learn about different types of housing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Toronto is huge and wildly different; you can find completely different types of housing for rent. Here is an overview:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A condo. Usually, a condo is owned by a person, in rare cases by some company. There are two types of condo buildings: high-rise and low-rise. As I wrote above, these buildings also have some amenities, and the apartments, in general, look modern. We decided to rent a place in a high-rise building only if we don&amp;rsquo;t find anything else. But a condo as a type of rental housing was just right for us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rental apartments that are located in buildings that are owned by a company. Pros - you don&amp;rsquo;t need to communicate with a landlord if something needs to be fixed; cons - usually, the washer and a dryer are located in those buildings&amp;rsquo; basement. Also, we heard there might be bedbugs in such buildings. So we decided even not to consider such places, although they are in great demand among people who have just arrived in Canada.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basements - are my &amp;ldquo;favorite&amp;rdquo; type of rental housing here. If you see a house in Toronto, most probably someone lives in a basement there (and it&amp;rsquo;s not a homeless person!). They say homeowners rent out basements to pay for their mortgage, not sure if it&amp;rsquo;s true because often the first and the second floors are also rented out. Even though you&amp;rsquo;ll most likely have a backyard if you rent a basement, it&amp;rsquo;s dark inside, and come on.. it&amp;rsquo;s a basement! We did not consider the basements at all; it still seems to me that it is not very healthy to live there (particularly for the lungs).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The floor in a house or a whole house. Everything is clear here, the landlord will own the place, but since houses are larger than the condos, they&amp;rsquo;ll be more pricy. I always wanted to rent a house, but it didn&amp;rsquo;t fit into the budget at all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Townhouse. Usually, a townhouse is a detached house and only has neighbours from the side. It&amp;rsquo;s a bit different here; they basically call any apartment in two to three storeys buildings a townhouse. If it is located on the first floor, it most likely has a terrace; if it&amp;rsquo;s located on the last floor, it has an entrance to the roof. The second floor is not that lucky, there is nothing there 🙂. We would definitely rent a  townhouse, but they are pretty pricy in the areas where you can get without a car. I haven&amp;rsquo;t seen any decent townhouses for less than $3500 CAD.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-4---prepare-to-rent-a-place&#34;&gt;Step 4 - prepare to rent a place&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we finally got our documents to stay here in Canada legally, we could start preparations to rent a place. Why do you need to prepare everything in advance? Well, good places are rented out too quickly here, so you need to have all the documents on you by the time you want to actually rent a place. Here is a list of documents for those who come to Canada as a foreign worker:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An employment letter that states the salary. If you don&amp;rsquo;t have it, a valid job offer might also work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A work permit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A recommendation letter from a bank (we got one back in Russia).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And the most important thing - you should have enough money in your Canadian bank account. Firstly, to get a statement from a local bank that you have money, and secondly, so that you can make a deposit within 24 hours after signing the contract (I&amp;rsquo;ll talk more about it later).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some landlords also want to see your SIN, but it&amp;rsquo;s illegal, and you should not do it.
A few days after D. got employed here, we opened a bank account, transferred our funds from Russia, and got a check book that could be helpful later for rent payments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-5---actually-rent-a-place&#34;&gt;Step 5 - actually rent a place&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, when we got all the documents, we could start looking for a place. I should also mention that you can&amp;rsquo;t move out earlier than in a year when you rent a place in Toronto. If you do, you will still have to pay till the end of the lease period anyway. So it was vital for us to find a decent place where we would enjoy living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our relocation consultant introduced us to an agent would help us with all the lease related paperwork. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to pay for an agent here, the landlord does it even if you hired an agent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several sites where you can look for an apartment, but the most popular (in my opinion) are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.realtor.ca/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;realtor.ca&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://condos.ca/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;condos.ca&lt;/a&gt;. On condos.ca, you can also check the history of a particular apartment. For example, you can find the apartment&amp;rsquo;s price when it was rented out previously. Our agent Aine has also recommented &lt;a href=&#34;https://realestate.love/home?presented-by=00f1adb36bbd4841ab6b26ee7600d6dd&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;realestate.love&lt;/a&gt; app, if you register with this &lt;a href=&#34;https://realestate.love/home?presented-by=00f1adb36bbd4841ab6b26ee7600d6dd&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;, Aine will be assigned as your realtor, and she is great!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even before we moved to Toronto, we decided that we could afford to spend around $2500 CAD on rent. We wanted to rent a 2-bedroom apartment, because now when we work from home, we need a space for home office. They say that during the lockdown, real estate prices in the city have dropped significantly. But in fact, it hit the downtown condos mostly because people no longer need to live near offices, but unfortunately, it did not really affect other areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After we checked all of the areas mentioned above, we decided to look at the High Park area and everything around it (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Bloor&amp;#43;West&amp;#43;Village,&amp;#43;Toronto,&amp;#43;ON/data=!4m2!3m1!1s0x882b3687bf4111a9:0x547e7e8c155e92b1?sa=X&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwiUu-OL-c7uAhUHGFkFHTdZCCsQ8gEwNXoECCQQAQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bloor West&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/The&amp;#43;Junction,&amp;#43;Toronto,&amp;#43;ON/@43.6665206,-79.4794536,15z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x882b3423ddb31365:0x52d8c657a0a69c40!8m2!3d43.6655088!4d-79.4721328&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Junction&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/maps/place/High&amp;#43;Park&amp;#43;North,&amp;#43;Toronto,&amp;#43;ON/@43.6580291,-79.4749742,15z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x882b3426203a9f13:0x341044bd3bac1ae2!8m2!3d43.6572262!4d-79.4668306&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;High Park North&lt;/a&gt;). But due to the absence of high-rises (which is a pro), there were very few options available for rent (which is a con). I monitored rental sites for about a month (I looked for the sake of interest even before we could rent something) and rarely saw any options there. There are a lot of basements available but no condos. Finally, I saw a charming condo that met all our criteria: a 2-bedroom, low-rise building, bright place with a balcony. The price was $2700 CAD, and it was fine for us (everything that I really liked was above $3000 CAD anyway). We realized that the apartment was nice, the area was excellent (Junction, which is a little further from High Park than we planned, but it was still ok), and we immediately contacted our agent. I want to mention that there was a huge selection of apartments in high-rise buildings, but not so many in low-rise buildings in different areas. In fact, it was the only option that we liked in the whole city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday night, the landlord&amp;rsquo;s agent agreed to show us the place on Saturday morning. Despite a couple of cons, for example, there are no windows in one bedroom, and there is also no concierge in the house, we really liked the place, and we wanted to rent it badly. Speaking of the bedroom without the windows. It looks like the developers have found a way to trick the system into making a room with a glass sliding door that lets in enough light to be recognized by local regulations as a bedroom. Surprisingly developers here act like in Russia and gain maximum profit from every square meter.
The agent also warned us that some other people would also check the place on Sunday, so it would be better to send our offer to the landlord as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-6---survive-the-bureaucracy&#34;&gt;Step 6 - survive the bureaucracy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a timeline to clarify how difficult everything is here and how different from the usual renting process in St. Petersburg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday, 11 am. We checked the place, liked it and decided to rent it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday, 12 pm. Right after we checked the apartments, we got into the agent&amp;rsquo;s car (all cafes are closed here) and filled out our offer for renting an apartment (OREA Form 410), which our agent later added to Docusign for signing (it&amp;rsquo;s very cool that the entire document flow here can be done online). The landlord will only consider you as a tenant if they receive an offer from you (well, from their agent). In the offer, you need to add all tenants and occupants, your position and company details, previous place of residence, and two contacts in Canada as referrals. We only have one friend in Vancouver, so we added her, and we decided to add a friend from the USA.
Although usually, the rent starts on the 1st of the month, our possession date will be February 17. Current tenants occupy the place until February 15, so we decided to rent the apartment right after they leave. Basically, in our offer, we proposed to pay for a year and a few weeks on top and three months of deposits instead of the usual two months (our agent said that since we don&amp;rsquo;t have any credit history in Canada, it might help us to get the place). Then the agent got our documents altogether and emailed them to the landlord&amp;rsquo;s agent along with our offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday, 6 pm. We received an email from our agent saying that the other agent didn&amp;rsquo;t want to forward our offer to the landlord. They asked for a confirmation from D.&amp;rsquo;s company that he was employed there and passed a probation period. And since it was Saturday, they proposed to wait until Monday to get a response from the HR team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday, 7 pm. D. emailed both HR and the team lead and asked them to confirm his employment ASAP. It was complicated to confirm the probation period, though. He had already passed the probation period in Russia, but since he was a new employee here in Canada, HR were obligated to add another probation period to the contract. Moreover, that agent shouldn&amp;rsquo;t even ask about the probation period since it&amp;rsquo;s a piece of confidential information. Our agent just assumed that the landlord&amp;rsquo;s agent didn&amp;rsquo;t want to do any paperwork on the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sunday, 7 pm. Our agent told us that other people who also checked the condo made an offer, and she assumed that they offered $2800 CAD. We got really sad, but the agent said it was a typical situation in Toronto, and, if we wanted, we could raise our offer to $2900 CAD. She said that $2900 CAD was the initial price for that place before COVID, and it really might help. We rechecked the real estate websites, realized there was nothing new, and decided to go with a new price (although, as I previously mentioned, our initial limit was $2500 CAD). We were also worried that the landlord&amp;rsquo;s agent wouldn&amp;rsquo;t even forward our offer to the landlord, but our agent assured us that they were obligated by law to forward all offers they received.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monday, 3 pm. The landlord chose us! We were thrilled that our (mine) misery during the weekend was not in vain (well, as usual, I didn&amp;rsquo;t sleep and didn&amp;rsquo;t eat well). Our agent immediately warned us that when the landlord signs the offer, the apartment is &amp;ldquo;frozen&amp;rdquo; on the market; roughly speaking, they have no right to show or lease it to anyone. Then the most interesting thing began - they sent us a 20 pages contract, we signed it. And then, the landlord&amp;rsquo;s agent added an appendix B to the contract, yet another 20 pages long. As our agent said, everything in the add-on looked like we were renting a house, not a condo, i.e., they wanted to add as much as possible into the contract to keep themselves safe (I can understand it, but some things were just crazy). Some statements were completely contrary to the law of the state of Ontario, which means they had no legal value. For example, it stated that no pets were allowed in the apartment (we don&amp;rsquo;t have any pets, though). Well, everyone in Ontario is allowed to have pets; in fact, a gorgeous kitty lives in this apartment at the moment 😸.
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://natashakatson.com/images/cat.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;кот&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

Another &amp;ldquo;cool&amp;rdquo; thing was about the carpet. &amp;ldquo;The Tenant agrees to employ carpets for frequent walking areas in order to prevent noise
distribution and floor deterioration.&amp;rdquo; Our agent told us that this part usually applies to the houses, but not to the condos.
Generally, we wanted to remove some statements from the contract, but then we learned how it works. We can either accept the contract and sign as is or reject and ask to send a new contract with the desired changes. But, if you reject the current contract (i.e., just ask to change any statements there), the apartment is again open to the market, and at that moment, someone can make another offer, which may be better than ours, and in this case, we would lose our apartment. So we agreed with everything and signed the contract as is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After both parties have signed the contract, you as a tenant have one working day to make a deposit. The apartment is considered to be leased the moment the landlord&amp;rsquo;s brokerage receives the deposit. The deposit does not go directly to the landlord to protect all parties from fraud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday morning, we went to the bank to make a deposit. We had two options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To electronically wire the funds, but this option costs an additional $17.50 CAD;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To deliver a bank draft in person to the bank, which is free. We chose this option, went to our bank, got a check, made a picture of it (in case the other bank loses it, yes, it happens!), and delivered the check to another bank.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday afternoon, we sent the picture of the check to our agent, and after a few hours got an update that the brokerage received our deposit. At that moment, we officially rented that condo!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hurray, now we need to wait for February 17 and get the keys. Not yet :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-7---do-a-million-more-things-to-get-the-keys-to-the-apartment&#34;&gt;Step 7 - do a million more things to get the keys to the apartment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After our agent congratulated us on a successful deal (she knew how we were worried and periodically called me to find out how I felt 🥲), we received an email from our relocation consultant with the next steps. In order for the landlord to give us the keys, we had to do a few more things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Purchase tenant&amp;rsquo;s insurance. We called different companies for a quote but then learned that D&amp;rsquo;s company provides a TD Insurance discount. We had to add liability coverage for $1 000 000 CAD based on our lease, and we also added some water damage coverage. After the discount, the final price was $405 CAD, including tax.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had to move the electricity and water account over to our names. That was easy; we just registered on the website which our consultant has provided us with. Starting from February 17, we will have access to our account.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contact our landlord regarding the payment method. We had two options again:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Email transfer. We preferred this option, but RBC has a $2500 CAD limit per day for any transfers, and it&amp;rsquo;s not enough for us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Post-dated checks.  So we chose this option since we also already got the checks when we opened an account.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prepare a personal check for $300 CAD refundable key deposit (yes, if we lose our keys, we would have to pay $300 CAD for it).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And my favorite part is that we have to reserve an elevator for our move with building management (it&amp;rsquo;s just something very new to us!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-epilogue&#34;&gt;An epilogue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have read up to this point, my congratulations to you 😂🥳. I&amp;rsquo;m thrilled that we managed to rent the apartment that we liked and in the area where we wanted to live. The only thing we absolutely forgot to do was to check if there were any shelters in the area. There are many mentally sick homeless people in Toronto, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to interact with them, and having a shelter nearby means they will continuously hang around. I just remembered this yesterday and discovered that there is the second-largest shelter in Toronto for homeless women not far from the condo building. I was very upset, but let&amp;rsquo;s hope that everything will be fine there because after all the area is still considered quite nice and even trendy 😏.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also want to say that I honestly admire those who come to Canada without work and any help. I can say that the consultant helps a lot by telling us what to do and when. When you first come across such an ordinary situation as renting an apartment, you get a little crazy about everything that needs to be done in a new country. I immediately remembered how we moved out of our apartment in St. Petersburg. We told our landlord about us leaving two weeks before we moved out. We told her that our friends wanted to move in, introduced them, and they paid us the deposit that she owned us, not to bother the landlord once again. Haha, here they probably only write about it in fairy tales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still have the feeling that it&amp;rsquo;s all scam before we actually get the keys. Oh, I need to get rid of this post-Russian habit of seeing a fraud everywhere or at least relax for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Get Your SIN in Canada</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.com/posts/get-your-sin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 14:54:18 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.com/posts/get-your-sin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Finally, we have all the necessary documents (work permit, to be specific) to proceed with further bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is how the process usually works. A person lands in Canada with a work visa (let&amp;rsquo;s say during the COVID pandemic). After the arrival, they get a Work Permit at the airport and take a two-week quarantine, which I &lt;a href=&#34;https://natashakatson.github.io/ru/posts/quarantine/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;mentioned&lt;/a&gt; earlier. While they in quarantine, they can apply online for a SIN (social insurance number0, contact a bank to get an account, and get employed remotely with their Work Permit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, the minimum required documents before you can start looking for an apartment are: SIN, a bank account, employment confirmation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we spent a month and a half in Canada in the &amp;ldquo;waiting&amp;rdquo; status and only got Work Permits a few days ago, we couldn&amp;rsquo;t apply anywhere. Therefore, as soon as we received the Work Permit on January 11, we immediately started to work on further steps. And we started with a SIN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our relocation package also included a local consultant, so we have been assigned with a consultant named M. who would help us with local affairs upon our arrival. M. advised us to apply for a SIN online. For some reason, to apply online, one needs either an employment letter (and the company will only hire D. on January 20) or a confirmation address (and we don&amp;rsquo;t have a permanent address yet). Also, some people who applied online bragged about their SIN being lost in the mail. And it takes them a month to issue a SIN for those who apply online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We decided that M.&amp;rsquo;s advice to apply online was, of course, a good one, and we would use it if necessary. But we decided to try to go to the Service Canada office first (offline). We checked the addresses for open offices &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.servicecanada.gc.ca/tbsc-fsco/sc-dsp.jsp?rc=3591&amp;amp;lang=eng&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and decided to try our fortune (I already forgot what does this word even mean..fortune). I find it funny that they say on the website that the shortest waiting time is from 8:30 till 10:00 am. We went there at 8:30, and we were the only ones. How does it work? If people read that there are no lines during these hours, why don&amp;rsquo;t they go there exactly from 8:30 - 10:00 am? :) It&amp;rsquo;s a rhetorical question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;here-is-a-cool-story&#34;&gt;Here is a cool story&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you read a previous &lt;a href=&#34;https://natashakatson.github.io/ru/posts/welcome-to-canada/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;, you probably know that our passports got stamped only on January 11 (the same as Work Permit).
Here we are at Service Canada; I start talking with the representative and giving her my passport and Work Permit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The representative: [shocked]. Omg, did you arrive in Canada the day before yesterday?! &lt;br&gt;
Me: [also shocked for a sec] Oh, no, no, no, no! We arrived on December 3.&lt;br&gt;
She: But your passport was stamped on January 11! You should quarantine at home!&lt;br&gt;
Me: No, no, no, no, no! We arrived on December 3, we quarantined, but they only issued our Work Permits and stamped our passports on January 11.&lt;br&gt;
She: ..but where did you get your Work Permit and a stamp?!&lt;br&gt;
Me: At the airport, we got back there after the quarantine because we had an appointment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She listened and immediately asked about some confirmation to make sure that we arrived on December 3. Of course, we didn&amp;rsquo;t have any proof: the Officer took our appointment paper; the ArriveCan app doesn&amp;rsquo;t store history (wtf?!); nobody signed the declaration form that we filled out at the plane, and we didn&amp;rsquo;t have our tickets on us. But then we remembered that we do have a copy of the appointment paper in the email, so we showed it. The representatives at Office Canada believed us but couldn&amp;rsquo;t issue a SIN. The system said that we should stay at home for two weeks and shouldn&amp;rsquo;t walk around to get our documents. But then a miracle happened, we finally met friendly people. Those women told us not to worry, that they really wanted to help us and would do their best to do so. And, after half an hour and a talk with their manager, they issued us our SINs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you need to get a SIN, I strongly recommend going directly to the Service Canada office. One of the perks is that they do not require any proof of address; Work Permit and a passport should be enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S. After my previous experience, I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect to meet friendly people at the Government office (I even left a nice review on Google Maps). On the way home, some construction worker said &amp;ldquo;good morning&amp;rdquo; and smiled. Later on the same day, we opened bank accounts, but without a credit card yet (you need an employment letter to get one). I even managed to finally get a sim card (e sim) at &lt;a href=&#34;https://referme.to/nataliiak-30n&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Fido&lt;/a&gt; and used one of their promos on time (12 G.B. for $55 which is still a lot but it&amp;rsquo;s cheaper than the usual $75 for 12 G.B.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turned out to be a productive and enjoyable day. Isn&amp;rsquo;t that wonderful?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Day When We Finally Got a Work Permit</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.com/posts/welcome-to-canada/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 20:27:05 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.com/posts/welcome-to-canada/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today is the 11th of January, which means that we have to go to the airport to check if there are any news regarding our &lt;a href=&#34;https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/hello-canada/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;case&lt;/a&gt;. I had insomnia, couldn&amp;rsquo;t eat in the morning, but we finally went to the airport to be there by 2:30 pm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CBSA office looks similar to the police station (I haven&amp;rsquo;t been at any, but I see it that way). The Officer on duty got our documents and checked if we were who we said we were. He looked at D.&amp;rsquo;s copy of the passport, looked at me, and said: &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s not you&amp;rdquo;. Of course, it&amp;rsquo;s not me; it&amp;rsquo;s my husband&amp;rsquo;s ID you are looking at, Officer. Then he asked us about our story, and when we told him, he got confused. He asked D.: &amp;ldquo;How will I know that it&amp;rsquo;s you and not your tween brother?&amp;rdquo; I kind of wanted to cry when I heard this question. Really? Really? How about checking all the supporting documents and biometrics for a change. Then we told him that we have been waiting for a month and a half already, and we really wanted to hear their answer on our case. We also mentioned the last name of the first officer we met upon our arrival here, and luckily he was at the airport that day. The Officer on duty took our documents and went to talk to Officer J. (the one who met us upon our arrival).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After an hour, Officer J. came to us and said there was still no reply from the visa office, but our lawyer convinced him to issue our documents! So, Officer J. decided to issue D. a temporary resident permit, and because of that, he could issue a temporary work permit. Actually, we asked him for the exact same documents when we arrived, but he refused back then. Luckily (we are very grateful), he eventually issued us our papers and gave our passports back with the stamp! We spent an additional $440 CAD ($155 for a new work permit, $200 for a temporary residence permit, $85 for a new biometric). Of course, we didn&amp;rsquo;t care about the prices; we were just happy to stay here in Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They stamped our passports with today&amp;rsquo;s date, which means that we left St.Petersburg on the 3d of December 2020 and arrived in Toronto on the 11th of January, 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a terribly exhausting and rather useless time, but we are happy that bureaucratic situation was resolved in our favor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, now, we can start to deal with life.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quarantine in Toronto </title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.com/posts/quarantine/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 15:26:31 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.com/posts/quarantine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While I have some free time, I want to tell you about the quarantine in Canada, specifically in Toronto. Before we went to Canada, we read this &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.canada.ca/en/public-health/services/publications/diseases-conditions/2019-novel-coronavirus-information-sheet.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; about the 14 days of mandatory quarantine for everyone entering Canada. As requested, we prepared a quarantine plan to share with the Officer, but we haven&amp;rsquo;t talked much about the quarantine itself because of our &lt;a href=&#34;https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/hello-canada/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;unusual case&lt;/a&gt;. The Officer just told us to go to our temporary place and be back at the airport when the quarantine is over. I was actually mentally prepared for the quarantine; what I was not prepared for was our situation. But I won&amp;rsquo;t talk about it today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We got Uber and went directly to our place in downtown Toronto. D.&amp;rsquo;s company rented apartments there in a tall condo building. We knew nothing about the place; we just hoped it would have a balcony so we could &amp;ldquo;walk around and get some air.&amp;rdquo; It appeared to be nice furnished apartments with cooking supplies and everything a person needs to stay at home. It also had a balcony with a view on a small park.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://natashakatson.com/images/2021-01-03.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we arrived, the receptionist told us about the quarantine and added us to the &amp;ldquo;quarantine list,&amp;rdquo; which allowed them to leave the deliveries at our door. Usually, they would ask the residents to pick up the deliveries at the reception (because of Covid). The quarantine means that you should not leave your apartments even if you need to take out the trash. We usually called a company which owned our suit in advance to ask them to take out our trash, put the trash next at our door, and some person picked it up. Every morning we checked-in in the ArriveCan app, which you need to install before going to Canada; either way, they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t let you on board. If you forget to check-in, you&amp;rsquo;ll get a reminder about it. On the 15th day, our profile got reset, and we could finally go outside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now I&amp;rsquo;ll share details about some delivery services that we used to survive the quarantine. There are many deliveries here, but it&amp;rsquo;s not easy to quickly get around them with a full understanding of prices and fees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TL;DR The cheapest way is to order a lot of items directly from the Grocery store. But because of our situation, we were not sure how many things we should order because we didn&amp;rsquo;t know if we would stay here in Canada. So we tried different options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;grocery-delivery&#34;&gt;Grocery Delivery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;uber-eats&#34;&gt;Uber Eats&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next morning after we arrived, we were too hungry to look around for new apps, we had to quickly order something. We were already familiar with &lt;a href=&#34;https://ubereats.app.link/LfdZFuf8Kcb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Uber Eats&lt;/a&gt;. The grocery delivery in Uber Eats is actually powered by Cornershop (I will tell about it further) and is done within 1-2 hours. Eventually, Uber Eats turned out to be the most expensive grocery delivery because we paid both the Uber Eats fee and the Cornershop fee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the summary of our first order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Walmart (grocery itself)&lt;/strong&gt; CA $132.03&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cornershop service CA $13.20&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivery CA $6.90&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Estimated taxes CA $4.47:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product taxes CA $1.85&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Service fee taxes CA $1.72&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivery fee taxes CA $0.90&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Order total&lt;/strong&gt; CA $156.60&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it&amp;rsquo;s pretty expensive, but it&amp;rsquo;s ok when you are hungry, stressed out, and can&amp;rsquo;t go out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later I found out that Uber has recently bought Cornershop, but you can still order groceries directly in Cornershop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cornershop&#34;&gt;Cornershop&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://corner.shop/r/oypnskrr4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Cornershop&lt;/a&gt; also deliver groceries within 1-2 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can order groceries from various supermarkets: Walmart, Costco, Longos, Metro, etc. You also get three free deliveries after the registration. For some reason, they also gifted me a $20 discount, maybe because I added some items to the basket but didn&amp;rsquo;t order them right away. Even though Cornershop charges a 10% service fee for every order, it&amp;rsquo;s still cheaper than Uber Eats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the summary of our first order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Walmart&lt;/strong&gt; $79.40&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cornershop service $7.90&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivery Fee Free&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Estimated taxes: $4.04
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product taxes $3.01&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Service fee taxes $1.03&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Credits applied -$20.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt; $71.38&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We later ordered groceries from Cornershop a few more times, I also shared a referral with my husband, and after we placed an order from his account, I got $20 off for my next order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please note that if some items are out of stock, they will suggest a replacement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;walmart&#34;&gt;Walmart&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another delivery that we tried was Walmart delivery. The downside is that you have to place your order a few days before the actual delivery date. But even after you place your order, you can still manage your basket. For example, the delivery was set for noon, but I could change items in my basket until 10 pm of the previous day. Walmart doesn&amp;rsquo;t charge you for service fee, the standard delivery costs $7.97, but you can order the same-day delivery for $10. Unfortunately, if some items are out of stock, you can&amp;rsquo;t choose the replacement; they will do it for you. But if you don&amp;rsquo;t like it, you can always return it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the summary of our first order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Items Subtotal&lt;/strong&gt;: $130.77&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivery fee :  $7.97&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HST @ 13%:  $2.20&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;: $140.94&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;instacart&#34;&gt;Instacart&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last but not least grocery delivery that I want to mention is &lt;a href=&#34;https://inst.cr/t/YjVsWUdYMTBu&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Instacart&lt;/a&gt;. My referral link will give you a $10 discount for your first order. I also used a referral link when I signed up, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t order items from my basket right away..And I got $20 off the next day :) The delivery costs around 5% of the order summary. I liked it that they contacted me in their virtual chat about the items that were out of stock; this way, it was easier for me to find a replacement. As I previously mentioned, Uber Eats and Cornershop do the same thing, but Instacart representative contact you directly in live chat, which is nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Summary:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Item Subtotal: $93.62&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sales Tax: $0.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tip: $4.68&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Service Fee: $4.68&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bags Fee: $0.30&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Retailer Coupon Discount: -$20.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total: $83.89&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the products were carefully packed, the delivery person left the bags right by the door, knocked, and left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;food-delivery&#34;&gt;Food delivery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from cooking our meals, we also wanted to try various local restaurant deliveries, especially given that Toronto is famous for a variety of cuisine from all over the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We mostly used Uber Eats and DoorDash during our quarantine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;uber-eats-1&#34;&gt;Uber Eats&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ubereats.app.link/LfdZFuf8Kcb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Uber Eats&lt;/a&gt; has a much more variety of restaurants compared to DoorDash. They also have different discounts and personalized offers, for example, the &amp;ldquo;order one, get one free&amp;rdquo; deal. Although it should be the same meal to use this option, we left a comment for a restaurant to make one meal spicier than another one when we ordered from a Thai restaurant. Please note that the price for the meal is usually lower than it actually costs. For example, you want to order Massaman Curry, the price is $21, but you &lt;strong&gt;have to&lt;/strong&gt; add meat/seafood and rice to the order, and you have to separately pay for it. In the end, the &amp;ldquo;order one get one free&amp;rdquo; deal is only applied to Masaman Curry ($21) and is not applied to the additional stuff. There are also different fees applied to the order, like taxes, tips, and service fees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an example of our first order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Massaman Curry&lt;/strong&gt; CA $21&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shrimp CA $4.00&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jasmine Rice CA $0.00 (usually it&amp;rsquo;s not free, though)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tax CA $3.93&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Service Fee CA $4.20&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delivery Fee $0.99&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tips CA $5.11&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt; CA $39.23&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, although the Curry costs $21, we had to pay $39.12 in total. We later noticed that we could modify the tip, but I advise you to leave good tips because it&amp;rsquo;s a pandemic going on, and delivery people are our heroes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Useful tip&lt;/strong&gt;. You can get a free one month trial for Uber Eats (Eats Pass) and get free delivery in addition to 5% off from the orders that are more than $15. I eventually subscribed for Eats Pass for a month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;doordash&#34;&gt;DoorDash&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://drd.sh/iVyp4q/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Doordash&lt;/a&gt; is an Uber Eats competitor. It seemed to me that there are fewer restaurant options in it, but there are promotions, and delivery is often cheaper. DoorDash also has a subscription with some discounts. As a new user, you will get some bonuses - free shipping and some other discounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is my first order from DoorDash:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Subtotal&lt;/strong&gt; $30.58&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tax $4.42&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivery Fee Free&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Service Fee $3.36&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discount -$5.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tip $2.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt; $35.36&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;alcohol-delivery&#34;&gt;Alcohol delivery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also order alcohol in Toronto. We used &lt;a href=&#34;https://runnerinc.page.link/DgAEw6CcoQtk2sp78&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Runner&lt;/a&gt;, the delivery usually took around two hours after the order was placed. To get your first order, you have to show your ID for them to make sure that you are over 19 years old. The delivery person from Runner was literally the only person we saw during 14 days of quarantine. After they confirm your ID, they would just leave a package by the door, knock and leave for every other delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We ordered twelve bottles of beer and two bottles of wine for our first delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Item total&lt;/strong&gt; $86.58&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivery Fee $9.99&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tax $4.24&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tip $5.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt; 103.87&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-deliveries&#34;&gt;Other deliveries&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sure everyone knows about weed legalization in Canada. We were exhausted and devastated because of our situation, so we could not help but take advantage of it. Most of the deliveries need you to stop by the shop to show your ID, but some of them accept ID&amp;rsquo;s during the first delivery, for example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ocs.ca/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;OCS&lt;/a&gt; (looks like we saw two people during our quarantine, from Runners and OCS). Delivery was not so fast; it took them 2-3 days. We ordered a PAX vaporizer and some pods with a high level of CBD extracts to finally relax and get some sleep. The PAX costs $46.50, one pod costs around $50 on average (but it will last for half a year).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subtotal $96.45, including $11.00 tax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delivery Fee $0.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, of course, Amazon. Amazon.ca is not as great as amazon.com, but you can still order almost anything with a fast delivery. For example, cleaning supplies. I subscribed to Amazon Prime to have 1-day delivery, which is also free for the first month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we were really missing during the quarantine was the PlayStation! We sold ours just before the trip in order to buy a new one here after the arrival. But again, we couldn&amp;rsquo;t do it because we were not sure if they let us stay here..and to be honest, where can you order PlayStation 5?! They are still not available anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, quarantine is a great time to read about everything that you need to get done after it ends (banks, contracts for mobile providers, renting an apartment), but to be honest, we didn&amp;rsquo;t research much since we were under terrible stress. Once a day, we went out to the balcony to &amp;ldquo;walk,&amp;rdquo; several times a week, we worked out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, you can survive 14 days quarantine, but it&amp;rsquo;s pretty easy to get mad. Perhaps the most unusual feeling is the understanding that you have been in a completely new country and a city for two weeks but have not yet seen anything except the view from your window. I really appreciated people who walked the dogs; I usually spent a few hours a day looking at them 🐶.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S. We paid for everything using our Russian &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tinkoff.ru/sl/7WyfhoLwreO&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Tinkoff bank&lt;/a&gt;, which lets you have a CAD balance on your card. Once the quarantine was over, our spending on groceries got less since we were not obligated to order everything, and thus we could spend less on delivery fees. Also, take outs usually give you great discounts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Story About One Almost Successful Relocation</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.com/posts/hello-canada/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 21:19:57 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.com/posts/hello-canada/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello, my name is Natasha, and I&amp;rsquo;m a person who plans everything, but nothing goes according to my plan because of very different circumstances (and then I suffer and get depressed). I always wanted to move from Russia. I had plenty of ideas, thoughts, and sometimes opportunities to do that, but it never really happened until this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Immigration and relocation is not an easy process, especially during a pandemic. I am sure that many of those who relocated have 1001 stories about how they moved, but ours is just very weird and unusual. I don&amp;rsquo;t even know where to start because I can&amp;rsquo;t share one part of this story (although it deserves special attention), so I&amp;rsquo;ll start somewhere in the middle but will capture the background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in April 2019, I started planning a relocation to Amsterdam with the company I worked in (a huge and pretty popular tech company). From that time, I lived in the &amp;ldquo;waiting mode&amp;rdquo; (I decided not to buy an apartment, didn&amp;rsquo;t rent a new apartment, and so on). Although the relocation paperwork process has not yet been launched, there have already been some agreements. In the fall of 2019, my husband and I even went to Amsterdam to check it out once again, talk to my uncle, who has been living there for more than 20 years, reviewed everything related to health insurance and what&amp;rsquo;s not.
And then a lot of things happened that did not depend on me, and I never went to Amsterdam. In fact, as I wrote at the beginning, I have been living in this &amp;ldquo;waiting mode&amp;rdquo; almost my whole life. I was always almost moving somewhere, but things happened in the last moments, and I didn&amp;rsquo;t move. I was very tired of living in this feeling, I really wanted to move, and I had the opportunity to go to Canada with my husband&amp;rsquo;s (D.) work. And now the story begins!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We managed to get our visas right before COVID happened and a few weeks before they started to close all the borders. So we got stuck in Russia with valid work visas. In general, even then, although it caused my emotional disbalance and regular tears, it gave me the hope that while we were waiting, something might change, and we could still move to Amsterdam. While the borders were closed, D. decided to change his last name. He wanted to do it for a long time; he had his reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, before even starting to apply for a new last name, we consulted with the immigration lawyers who handled the entire moving process. They said that he could go ahead and change his last name; there should be no issues since The USA and Canada usually allow people to enter the country with a valid visa even if it has an old last name. The main thing is that it is still the same person. While the process of changing the last name was in progress, Canada opened its borders and allowed it to enter the country for those who have work visas. When D. finally received all the new documents, he wrote an email to the lawyers to inform them that we were ready to fly. The first thing that surprised me was that the lawyers thought we had been in Canada for a long time already and that he was changing the last name inside the country.  Well, fine, in general, they told us again that everything was ok, but if we were too worried, we could write an email to the visa office to find out if they could re-issue the visa into a new passport. Unfortunately, the Visa Office said they would not do it, and if we want to get a new visa, we need to re-apply.
It took us a couple of weeks to get a visa before Covid happened, and now the process can take up to six months, so the lawyers advised us to travel with the current documents because, as they said in advance, there should be no issues at the border. The only ones who might have questions were the airline company, so the lawyers prepared a document that explained the situation to prevent any problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let&amp;rsquo;s skip everything that I felt when I quit (it was terribly difficult and took me an endless number of sleepless nights), goodbyes, accepting the fact that we were not moving to Europe, but to another continent (although I dreamed about it very much, but the older I got, the more I wanted to go to Europe. Also I had a lot of friends and relatives there, and would be close to my parents).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the scariest part before the trip was not to get Covid, because, in addition to the fact that the Covid itself was already very bad, it would also postpone the trip once again (we have been in the &amp;ldquo;waiting stage&amp;rdquo; for a year already). Okay, I will drop this part of the story again, although I must admit that my nervous system could not stand it all, and I had to start taking tranquilizers to live through it all. I calmed myself down; I hoped that we would move soon, arrive, and finally, I could just relax and come to my senses after all the hell that I have gone through this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On December 1, the moving company has packaged all of our belongings. They prepared two containers: one would travel by air (it would take two weeks to arrive in Canada), another one would travel by sea (it would take two months to arrive). There were two suitcases left for us with some necessary things that we would take on board. It is also worth mentioning that on December 1, we discovered that Canada requires additional confirmation for a person who travels as a family (me), which I didn&amp;rsquo;t have, of course. The lawyers assured us that since we received our visas before Covid, that rule didn&amp;rsquo;t concern me since I would be traveling using a work visa with an open work permit (and this is very important!). Well, sure, although at that moment, I just wanted to fall into a medical coma before I land on the other continent. But, oh well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;point-1---stpetersburg-pulkovo&#34;&gt;Point 1 - St.Petersburg, Pulkovo&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We arrived at Pulkovo, showed our documents, and of course, as we expected, there were problems with the last name. The issue was not related to the visa itself; the system did not allow to print the boarding pass. In 20 minutes and with the help of the &amp;ldquo;main&amp;rdquo; computer, they printed the tickets. They asked us whether we would be allowed to enter Canada with a different last name, we showed a letter from our lawyer, and they let us go. The border control also had no questions. They only asked me for a reason for my trip. I said that it was for work, and when asked where I worked, I said that I work in Toronto, and it worked:) I have an open work permit, I don&amp;rsquo;t have to have a job to enter the country, but it would be too complicated for Russian board control officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;point-2---istanbul&#34;&gt;Point 2 - Istanbul&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a 9-hour layover in Istanbul. My ex-colleagues told me about the hotel right at the airport, so we could get some sleep. After getting enough sleep, we went to get ready to &amp;ldquo;fight&amp;rdquo; with the local control services. Because Canada does not let everyone in, the control at the gate was pretty serious. We showed all the documents, but of course, there were questions about the last name change. The person who checked our documents took pictures of them and sent them to someone in What’s app. He said that he sent it to the Canadian Immigration Services. We were not sure though it was legal to take a picture of documents, including a job offer with the salary, and send them to someone unknown in What’s app. They asked me if I was traveling as a spouse; I said &amp;ldquo;no&amp;rdquo; because I had a work visa. But again, oh well, just let us on board! The plane was departing at 3:45 pm; at 3:40 pm, we still did not know whether they would let us on board. In the end, that man called the Canadian Immigration Service, who asked if D. was the same person or not. After confirmed it, they told him to let us on board immediately. Exactly at 3:45 pm, we got on the plane, the doors closed right behind us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we relaxed for a bit; the most exhausting part was behind us.
We only worried about one thing - what if the Border Control Officer asks me for supporting documents. Eleven hours of flight in N-95 masks (plus the time of the first flight and the transfer), a swollen nose, and we finally landed in Toronto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;point-3---toronto&#34;&gt;Point 3 - Toronto&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We landed in Toronto around 7 pm. The first officer looked at our documents and said that everything was ok, we could go-ahead to get our work permits. And then something happened that no one expected at all. We provided the Officer with our documents and explained the situation with the last name change. He listened, it looked like everything was clear. He just wanted to make sure that the job offer was still valid (after all, the job offer was almost a year old, and he had to make sure that the company was still waiting for D.). We showed him a confirmation, and he asked us to wait for a while. An hour and a half later, he returned to us saying that he reviewed our documents, but he couldn&amp;rsquo;t issue a work permit because he didn&amp;rsquo;t want to issue it with a new last name because all the documents have the previous last name. And he didn&amp;rsquo;t want to issue the work permit with an old last name because D. had a new last name. Of course, he couldn&amp;rsquo;t issue me a work permit because I&amp;rsquo;m a dependent. So he emailed the visa office and asked them what to do next. He told us to go to the apartments and stay on quarantine for 14 days (as planned) while he would be waiting for a reply from a visa office. He also took our passports and asked us to come back to the airport after the quarantine would be over, when he would tell us if they could re-issue a new work permit here in Canada or ask us to go back to Russia to re-apply for a new visa from scratch. Well, that sounded horrible! We called the lawyer, and he was also shocked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we quarantined for 14 days, we didn&amp;rsquo;t know our status here in Canada. We wouldn&amp;rsquo;t even order many groceries since we didn&amp;rsquo;t know if we would stay here or not. It was insane and mindblowing. I felt horrible; every day, I woke up with the thought: “Is this the last day in Canada? I haven&amp;rsquo;t even seen the city ”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On December 17, the quarantine was finally over, but there were still no news. The lawyer, as he said, did everything he could (but nothing happened). Just in case we need to go back to Russia, we decided to go and see Niagara right after the quarantine because we did not know if they would leave us here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On December 21, we went back to the airport. Our Officer was not there, and another Officer told us that our case was still in progress and that we should wait for another two weeks and come back on January 11 (which is three weeks!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we continue to live in this weird status, unable to work, open bank accounts, and rent an apartment. Our belongings cannot be sent here to Canada because The Russian customs service needs a photo of the stamp in the passport (and we do not have passports). In general, it isn&amp;rsquo;t easy to relax in this situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S. According to the lawyers&amp;rsquo; plan, the Officer should have issued a work permit with an old last name by default, D. could start working here, and in the meantime, he would update the Work Permit.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>