<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Natasha&#39;s Journey</title>
    <link>https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Natasha&#39;s Journey</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 20:27:05 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Day When We Finally Got a Work Permit</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/welcome-to-canada/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 20:27:05 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/welcome-to-canada/</guid>
      <description>Today is the 11th of January, which means that we have to go to the airport to check if there are any news regarding our case. I had insomnia, couldn&amp;rsquo;t eat in the morning, but we finally went to the airport to be there by 2:30 pm.
CBSA office looks similar to the police station (I haven&amp;rsquo;t been there, but I see it that way). The Officer on duty got our documents and checked if we were who we said we were.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quarantine in Toronto </title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/quarantine/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 15:26:31 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/quarantine/</guid>
      <description>While I have some free time, I want to tell you about the quarantine in Canada, specifically in Toronto. Before we went to Canada, we read this article about the 14 days of mandatory quarantine for everyone entering Canada. As requested, we prepared a quarantine plan to share with the Officer, but we haven&amp;rsquo;t talked much about the quarantine itself because of our unusual case. The Officer just told us to go to our temporary place and be back when the quarantine is over.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Story About One Almost Successful Relocation</title>
      <link>https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/hello-canada/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 21:19:57 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://natashakatson.github.io/posts/hello-canada/</guid>
      <description>Hello, my name is Natasha, and I&amp;rsquo;m a person who plans everything, but nothing goes according to my plan because of very different circumstances (and then I suffer and get depressed). I always wanted to move from Russia. I had plenty of ideas, thoughts, and sometimes opportunities to do that, but it never really happened until this time.
Immigration and relocation is not an easy process, especially during a pandemic. I am sure that many of those who relocated have 1001 stories about how they moved, but ours is just very weird and unusual.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
